<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The parable of the Kingdom of heaven expounded, or, An exposition of the first thirteen verses of the twenty fifth chapter of Matthew by Han. Knollis.</title>
            <author>Knollys, Hanserd, 1599?-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47568</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10788833</idno>
  <idno type="VID">45884</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240892681</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing K719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28971</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10788833</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47568)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45884)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1387:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The parable of the Kingdom of heaven expounded, or, An exposition of the first thirteen verses of the twenty fifth chapter of Matthew by Han. Knollis.</title>
                  <author>Knollys, Hanserd, 1599?-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 135 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benjamin Harris,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Jesus Christ --  Parables.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXV, 1-13 --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:45884:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of the author</figDesc>
                  <head>The true and Lively Effigies of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>HAN: KNOLLIS</hi> Minister of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Gospell Aged 67. Yeares.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45884:1"/>
            <p>THE PARABLE OF THE KINGDOM OF HEAVEN EXPOUNDED.</p>
            <p>Or, An Exposition of the first thirteen Verses of the twenty fifth Chapter of <hi>Matthew.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 13.34.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>All these things spake Jesus to the Multitude in Parables, and without a Parable spake he not unto them.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 8.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Ʋnto you it is given to know the Mysteries of the kingdom of God, but to others in Parables, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Psal. 78.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I will open my mouth in a Parable: I will utter dark sayings of old.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Psal. 49 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will incline mine ear to a Parable.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Han. Knollis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benjamin Harris,</hi> and are to be sold at the <hi>Stationers</hi> Armes in <hi>Sweeting</hi> Rents, in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> near the Royal Exchange. 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45884:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45884:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>ARt thou a Professour? I intreat thee do not rest in the form of Godliness without the power thereof; that undid the foolish Virgins to Eternity. It's a vain thing for any person to seem to be Religious, and be not so in truth. The figtree that had leaves was Cursed by Christ, because it bare no fruit; And it suddainly wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered.</p>
            <p>Art thou a Believer? Ponder then what is propounded in this little Treatise, and search the Scriptures, whether what is therein affirmed be so, or not. I know but in part, yet am I willing to impart my
<pb facs="tcp:45884:3"/> knowledge for thy Edification. And if any truth here asserted, shall profit thy understanding, my earnest Request to thee is, that thou wilt give all the Glory to God.</p>
            <p>Art thou a Profane person, and One that dost scoff at the Doctrine of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Christ? then know, that yet a little while, and He that shall come will come, and will not tarry; But if (in the mean Time) thou dye in thy Sins, thou wilt be Damned to Eternity. Be serious there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Reading this little Book, it may be God will make it a Blessing to thy Soul, and then I have my End.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy souls friend</hi> Han. Knollys.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45884:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. XXV. 1.</hi> to the end of the <hi>thirteenth verse.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>1. Then shall the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven be likened unto ten Virgins, which took their Lamps, and went forth to meet the Bridegroom.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>2. And five of them were wise, and five were foolish.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>3. They that were foolish, took their lamps, and took no oyle with them.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>4. But the wise took oyle in their vessels with their lamps.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>5. While the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom tarryed, they all slumbered and slept.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>6. And at midnight there was a cry made, Behold, the Bridegroom cometh, go ye out to meet him.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="2" facs="tcp:45884:4"/>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>7. Then all those Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45884:4"/> arose and trimmed their lamps.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>8. And the foolish said unto the wise, Give us of your oyle, for our lamps are gone out.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>9. But the wise answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, saying, <hi>Not so,</hi> lest there be not enough to us and you; but go ye rather to them that sell, and buy for your selves.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>10. And while they went to buy, the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom came, and they that were ready, went in with him to the marriage, and the door was shut.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>11. Afterward came al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the other Virgins, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Lord, Lord, open to us.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>12. But he answered and said, Verily I say unto you, I know you not.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</cell>
                        <cell>13. Watch therefore, for ye know neither the day, nor the hour wherein the Son of man cometh.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Lord Jesus Christ being asked by his Disciples what shall be <hi>the sign of his coming,</hi> Ch. 24.3. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered and said <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>Iniquity shall abound and the love of many shall wax
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45884:4"/> cold,</hi> and ver. 21. <hi>Then shall be great Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, such as was not from the beginning of the world to this time, no, nor ever shall be.</hi> So the Apostle testified also, 2 Tim. 3.1. But saith our Saviour ver. 29. <hi>Immediately after the Tribulation of those days,</hi> ver. 30. <hi>Then shall appear</hi> (not the person but) <hi>the sign of the Son of Man in Heaven— And they shall see the Son of Man coming in the Clouds of Heaven with power and great Glory— Then shall the Kingdom of Heaven be likened to ten Virgins,</hi> Chap. 25.1.</p>
            <p>These thirteen verses contain a Parable and the Application of it to Christs Disciples. In the Parable are three General parts, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Parabolae</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ver. 1.-5. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ver. 6-9. And 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ver. 10.-13. And the Exhortation or Application of the Parable, in <hi>ver.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>In the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Parable observe 1. The time, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Then,</hi> that is when the Kingdom of God, and Coming of Christ in power and great glory is at hand, <hi>or near,</hi> even at the door: 2. The Subject or Matter that our Saviour spake of; <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> 3. The Resemblance thereof, <hi>Likened unto ten Virgins,</hi> who are described in this first verse by their preparation, <hi>They took their Lamps;</hi> and by their Action, <hi>They went out to meet the Bridegroom.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="verse">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45884:5"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Then shall the Kingdom of Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>By the Kingdom of Heaven in some places of the holy Scripture we are to understand the Kingdom of Glory, Matth. 5.3. <hi>Blessed are the poor in Spirit, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> In other places of Scripture by the Kingdom of Heaven, we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the spiritual Kingdom of Grace in the hearts of sanctified Believers, Matth. 13.31. <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven is like unto a grain of Mustard-seed.</hi> By the Kingdom of Heaven in some other places of Scripture we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the mystical Kingdom of the Church of Christ under the Gospel, Matth. 16.18, 19. <hi>Ʋpon this Rock</hi> (that Rock is Christ, 1 Cor. 10.4.) <hi>I will build my Church —. And I will give thee the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the Kingdom of Heaven in this verse we may not understand the Celestial King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Glory, for there are no foolish Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins in that Heaven, nor the spiritual King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Grace which is the Kingdom of God within us, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.21. But the Mystical Kingdom of the Church of God under the Gospel, wherein there are both wise and foolish Virgins.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Meditation.</hi> Every true visible Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Church of Christ under the Gospel did in the Apostles dayes and shall in the latter
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45884:5"/> dayes bear some resemblance unto the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven. For Confirmation of this Doctrine Read Isa. 60.1, 2, 3, 7, 13, 14, 15, 19, 22. <hi>The glory of the Lord shall arise upon thee and his glory shall be seen upon thee,</hi> ver. 2. <hi>I will glorifie the house of my glory,</hi> ver. 7. <hi>And I will make the place of my feet glorious,</hi> ver. 13. <hi>I will make thee an eternal Excellency,</hi> ver. 15. <hi>The Lord shall be unto thee an everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Light, and thy God thy Glory,</hi> ver. 19. <hi>I the Lord will hasten it in his time,</hi> ver. 22. that is, in Christs Day.</p>
               <p>In the Explication of this point two things are to be enquired into: 1. What is a true visible constituted Church of Christ un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Gospel: 2. Wherein the Church of God on Earth bears proportion with and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblance unto the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Touching the first particular, A true visible Constituted Church of Christ under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel is a Congregation of Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. Called out of the World, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7. Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from Idolaters and Idol Temples, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16, 17. from the unbelieving Jews and their Synagogues and all legal observations of holy dayes, Sabbath dayes, and Mosaical Rites, Ceremonies and shadows, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16, 17. and assembled together in one place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.23. On the Lords Day <hi>the first day of the Week,</hi> Acts 20.7. to worship
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45884:6"/> God visibly by the spirit and in the truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.23, 24. in the holy Ordinances of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. according to the saith and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Gospel, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.5.</p>
               <p>Touching the second particular to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into, it consists of two parts. 1. The Church is called a Kingdom. 2. The Church is called the Kingdom of Heaven. The Church is compared to a Kingdom: Because 1. Christ the head of the Church, is the King of Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.3. and the King of <hi>Zion, Psal.</hi> 2.6. <hi>and</hi> 149.1, 2. <hi>Let the Children of</hi> Zion (the Congregation of Saints, ver. 1.) <hi>be joyful in their King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Church of God is Christs Throne, Jer. 17.12. <hi>A glorious high Throne from the beginning</hi> (of his Mystical Kingdom) <hi>is the place of our Sanctuary,</hi> Rev. 4.4. <hi>A throne was set in Heaven,</hi> The Church, <hi>and ONE sate on the throne,</hi> namely Christ; <hi>And round about the Throne were twenty four Seats</hi> or Thrones; <hi>And upon the Seats I saw twenty four Elders</hi> (the spiritual Priests of God) <hi>sitting cloathed in white Raiment, and they had on their heads Crowns of Gold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Christ the King of his Church; is their Law-giver, <hi>Isa.</hi> 33.22. The Lord is our Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute-maker, and the Bible is his Statute-Book wherein are published all the Laws of Gods house, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.10, 11. according to which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45884:6"/> Laws the Church of Saints are to be governed by their Elders whom Christ hath set over them to Rule and Govern them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7, 17. according to the Laws of his house.</p>
               <p>The Church is compared to the Kingdom of Heaven, 1. with respect unto the gracious and glorious presence of God the Father, Son and holy Spirit in the Church: God dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in <hi>Zion, Psal.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Joel</hi> 3.21. for it is his Rest, <hi>Psal.</hi> 132.14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.20. <hi>For where two or three are gathered together in my Name, there am I in the midst of them.</hi> Rev. 2.1. <hi>Christ walketh in the midst of the Golden Candlesticks.</hi> Gods presence makes Heaven to be Heaven, and that makes a Heaven on Earth, a Heaven in the heart, and a Heaven in the Congregations of Saints.</p>
               <p n="2">2. With respect unto the spiritual glory of the Church of God in the later dayes, <hi>Isa.</hi> 60.7, 13. The Beauties of Holiness, <hi>Psal.</hi> 110.3. makes <hi>Zion</hi> the perfection of Beauty, <hi>Psal.</hi> 50.2. The Temple was filled with the Glory of God, Ezek. 43.5. &amp; 44.4. <hi>And the Glory of the Lord filled the House of the Lord.</hi> The house of the Lord is the Church of the living God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. And the Temple was filled with smoke from the glory of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.8.</p>
               <p n="3">3. With respect unto the great Company and number of Saints in the Assemblies and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45884:7"/> Churches of Christ (called the Churches of Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33.) among whom and in whose Assemblies are the holy Angels because of whose presence the Women were to be vailed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10. This will be more Evident in the last dayes, when the holy City the New <hi>Jerusalem</hi> shall come down from God out of Heaven, prepared as a Bride adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for her Husband, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1, 2, 3. And when we are come to Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> unto the City of the Living God, the Heavenly <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem,</hi> to the general Assembly and Church of the first born, and to Jesus the Mediatour of the new Covenant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23, 24. then will the Church of God on Earth bear some greater proportion with and resemblance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then shall the Kingdom of Heaven be likened unto ten Virgins,</hi> &amp;c. Ten is a Mystical num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as Dan. 7.7, 20, 24. <hi>ten horns,</hi> Jude 14. <hi>ten thousand of Saints,</hi> Rev. 2.10. <hi>ten dayes,</hi> and so ten Virgins; that is a <hi>definite</hi> number for an <hi>indefinite.</hi> By Virgins we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand Gospel Professors and Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, (2 Cor. 11.2. <hi>I have espoused you to one Husband that I may present you as a chast Virgin to Christ</hi>) who have escaped the pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the World through the knowledge of Christ, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. Some are foolish Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, formal professors denying the power of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45884:7"/> Godliness, only seeming to be Religious, <hi>James</hi> 1.26. who after they have escaped the Pollutions of the World through the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, are again entangled therein and overcome, whose later end is worse than their beginning, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20.</p>
               <p>Others who are wise Virgins having not only the form but the power of Godliness also, and being partakers of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have escaped the Corruption that is in the World through Lust, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. These being not defiled with spiritual Whoredoms do follow Christ wheresoever he goes, Rom. 14.4. <hi>These are they which are not defiled with Women</hi> (neither the <hi>great Whore</hi> of <hi>Rome, Mystery Babylon,</hi> the Mother of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1, 5. nor the <hi>Daughters</hi> of that Whore, <hi>false Churches,</hi> whose <hi>Mother</hi> My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical <hi>Babylon</hi> is, though some of those <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> be (as <hi>Nineveh</hi> was called, <hi>Nahum</hi> 3.4.) <hi>well-favoured Harlots,</hi> because of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of their spiritual Whoredoms.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Meditation.</hi> The Churches of Saints in the last dayes shall be reformed and restored unto a Virgin state of primitive purity and spiritual Glory, <hi>as in the Apostles dayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Confirmation of this Doctrine Read and Consider these Scriptures, <hi>viz.</hi> Isa. 2.2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>And it shall come to pass in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45884:8"/> last dayes that the Mountain of the Lords house shall be established in the top of the Mountains,</hi> &amp;c. Isa. 60.2, 3, 4, 5.6. <hi>He that is left in</hi> Sion <hi>and he that remaineth in</hi> Jerusalem <hi>shall be called holy,</hi> &amp;c. Isa. 60.17, 13, 21. <hi>I will glorifie the house of my Glory, and I will make the place of my feet glorious,</hi> &amp;c. Isa. 65.17, 18, 19, 25. <hi>For behold I create new Heavens and a new earth,</hi> &amp;c. Rev. 20.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Behold I make all things new,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.13, 14. Rev. 14.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>These are they that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Lamb — for they are Virgins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Explication of this point we are to consider two particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What Reformation will be in the Churches of Saints in the last dayes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What things shall be restored then which are or have been wanting in the Churches of Saints since the Apostles dayes.</p>
               <p>Touching the <hi>first</hi> particular, 1. Professors of the Gospel and Members of Churches will be much reformed from many Corruptions in their Judgements and Conversations. The Apostles tell us and foretold the Churches that in the later dayes some Professors would be corrupted in their Judgements; compare 1 Tim. 4.1, 2, 3. with 2 Pet. 2.1, 2, 3. <hi>And many shall follow their pernicious wayes, by reason of whom the way of truth shall be evil spoken of.</hi> And in the last dayes other Professors
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45884:8"/> would be corrupted in their Conversations 2 Tim. 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Covetous, proud, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise and Covenant Breakers, Lovers of pleasures more than Lovers of God, having a form of Godliness but denying the power thereof:</hi> and are not too too many members of Churches (<hi>who seem to be religious,</hi> Jam. 1.26.) very much corrupted in their Judgements, and some also in their Conversations? But the days are coming when there shall be a great Reformation in both these Respects.</p>
               <p>For God will return to the people a pure Language, Zeph. 3.9, 13. <hi>The Remnant of</hi> Israel <hi>shall not do iniquity nor speak lyes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall a deceitful tongue be found in their mouth.</hi> And those Virgin professors that follow the Lamb, Rev. 14.4, 5. <hi>shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the Earth,</hi> vers. 3. <hi>and from men,</hi> vers. 4. <hi>And in their mouth was found no guile, for they are without fault before the throne of God,</hi> vers. 5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Discipline and Government of the Churches will be very much reformed in the last days, for then Christ the <hi>LORD will Reign in Mount Sion, and in Jerusalem and before his Ancients gloriously,</hi> Mich. 4.6, 7. <hi>from henceforth even for ever.</hi> The Churches of Saints shall be ruled and Governed by the holy, Righteous and good Laws of the Lord Jesus Christ, <hi>Isa.</hi> 33.22. who is the Son over
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45884:9"/> the house of God, Heb. 3.1, 6. Ezek. 43.10, 11. <hi>Shew them all the Laws of the house and let them measure the Pattern,</hi> &amp;c. Isa. 9.6, 7. <hi>The Government shall lye upon his shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> Christ is the Legislator, the Law-giver, the Bible is his and his Churches Statute Book, and all the Churches, Ministers and Saints of God are to be governed by his Royal Law of Liberty, in obeying and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof there is a Blessing promised, <hi>James</hi> 1.25.</p>
               <p>Touching the second particular, 1. The Ministry of the Gospel will be restored in the later dayes, Jer. 13, 14, 15. <hi>I will bring you to Sion and I will give you Pastors according to my heart, they shall feed you with knowledge and with understanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The gifts of the holy spirit shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored in the last dayes, Joel 2.21, 23, 28, 29, 30 31. <hi>The LORD will do great things— Be glad then ye Children of Zion— I will pour out my spirit upon all flesh,</hi> &amp;c. Acts 2.17, 18. <hi>And it shall come to pass in the last dayes (saith God) I will pour out of my Spirit upon all flesh,</hi> &amp;c. This is that which God hath promised and will again perform.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Ordinances of God will be resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his Churches in the later dayes. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist hath made void the Commandments of God by the Traditions of men (as the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45884:9"/> Scribes and Pharisees did <hi>Mark</hi> 7.6, 7 9.) And he hath changed the Ordinances of Christ, and brought in the Ordinances of men, Col. 2.20, 22, 23. <hi>Why are ye subject to Ordinances</hi> (or Traditions) <hi>after the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and Doctrines of men,</hi> which is (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) will-worsh<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p, <hi>vers.</hi> 23. and vain worship, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15 8, 9. (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>But in vain do they worship me,</hi> &amp;c. The Ordinances of God (which have been corrupted by mens Inventions, and supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,) shall be restored to their primitive purity and first Institutions. Read <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.38. &amp; 30.40. and compare it with <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.5. Then will I turn to the people a pure Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage (or a <hi>clean Lip) that they may call upon the Name of the Lord and serve him with one shoulder</hi> (or consent.) <hi>In that Day the LORD shall be ONE, and his Name ONE;</hi> that is, in the later Days Christ and his Saints shall be ONE Kingdom: and his way and worship but ONE in all the Earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which took their Lamps.</hi> The Virgin Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors of the Gospel and Worshippers of God in the Churches of Christ have Lamps, <hi>that is,</hi> the presence of God in his Worship and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; Matth. 18.20. <hi>For where two or three are gathered together in my name,</hi> saith Christ, <hi>there am I in the midst of them.</hi> So
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45884:10"/> God manifested his presence with <hi>Abraham</hi> when he was offering a Sacrifice to the Lord, Gen. 15.17, 18. <hi>Behold a smoaking furnace and a burning Lamp, passed between those pieces; And God made a Covenant with Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi> Read <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.18, 27. &amp; 20.11. &amp; <hi>Isa.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.9. God appointed seven Lamps to be lighted and supplyed with sweet Oyle of Olives, both in his Wilderness Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.37. and in his <hi>Canaan</hi> Temple, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.20, 21. that they might burn continually before the Lord, which typed forth the seven Spirits of God, Rev. 3.1.4, 5. <hi>And there were seven Lamps of Fire burning before the throne which are the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven spirits of God,</hi> that is, the variety and abundance of the Gifts and Fruits of the Holy Eternal Spirit. There are diversity of Gifts, but the same Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4. and so there are divers and many fruits of the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>These ten Virgins having received their Lamps,</hi> to wit, a commandment from the Lord (for the Commandment is a Lamp, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.23.) to worship him by the Spirit in Truth, and Spiritual Gifts and Grace to perform the Gospel Instituted Ordinances of Christ ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the holy Will of God revealed in his written word; <hi>for his Word is a Lamp,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45884:10"/> unto the feet of his Saints, and a Light unto their Paths,</hi> Psal. 119.105.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Meditation.</hi> The Virgin Professors of the Gospel and Worshippers of God in the Churches of Saints shall have Gospel Light and Spiritual Gifts in the later dayes to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God in the Order and Ordinances of the Gospel according to the written Word of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> Virgin Professors shall have Gospel Light in the later dayes to worship God aright. The written Word of God <hi>(through the teachings of the holy Spirit)</hi> to wit, the commands of Christ and the Examples of his Apostles, Churches, and Saints approved by Christ <hi>(recorded in the holy Scripture of Truth)</hi> will be a Lamp and a Light unto them, <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.105. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1, 2.14.37. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>&amp; Isa.</hi> 60.1, 2, 3. <hi>Arise, shine, thy Light is come— And the Gentiles</hi> (or Heathen Nations) <hi>shall come to thy Light,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Virgin Professors in the Churches of Christ in the later Dayes shall have spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Gifts qualifying and inabling them to worship God by the Spirit and in the Truth in the Order and Ordinances of the Gospel, Acts 2.17. <hi>And it shall come to pass (saith God) in the last Dayes, I will pour out my spirit upon all flesh,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 12.4. <hi>There are Diversities of Gifts, but the same spirit.</hi> As
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45884:11"/> in the Dayes of the Apostles so shall it be in the last Dayes, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.21, 28, 29. much more poured forth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And went forth to meet the Bridegroom.</hi> This Bridegroom is the Lord Jesus Christ, Joh. 3.29 <hi>He that hath the Bride is the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom,</hi> that is, Jesus Christ, to whom his Churches and Saints are espoused, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. whom Christ hath betrothed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in loving kindness and faithfulness for ever, <hi>Hosea</hi> 2.19, 20. They are his Sister and his Spouse, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.10. The Lambs Wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7, 8. And He is the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, Isa. 62.5. <hi>With the Joy of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom over the Bride shall the LORD rejoice over thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To meet the Bridegroom, doth imply two things. <hi>First,</hi> That the Virgins did know and believe that Christ was coming, Psal. 96.9 11, 13. <hi>O worship the Lord in the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of holiness. Let the Heavens rejoice, and let the Earth be glad and rejoice before the Lord, for he cometh, for he cometh,</hi> &amp;c. Had not the foolish Virgins known and Believed that Christ would come, yea and that he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they would not have gone out to meet him, but would rather have scoffed at his coming, when the wise Virgins had spoken of it, as <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ose Scoffers will do, 2 Pet. 3.3, 4. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>re shall come in the last Dayes Scoffers—
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45884:11"/> saying where is the promise of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That all the Virgins did know and believe, That the coming of the spiritual Bridegroom Christ Jesus was near, and that he would come quickly or shortly: The Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grooms coming was even at the Door, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they went out to meet him, Heb. 10.37. <hi>Yet a little while and HE that shall come will come, and will not tarry. Now the Just shall live by Faith.</hi> The Virgins believed this and went out to meet the Bridegroom, and they had Scripture ground to believe it, because Christ had revealed it in his written word, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12. Behold I come quickly, <hi>vers.</hi> 20. <hi>HE which testifieth these things saith surely I come quickly,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>They went out to meet the Bridegroom, <hi>that is,</hi> The Virgin Professors in the Churches of Saints in the later dayes knowing and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the Coming of Christ the Bridegroom, will go out from their nearest and dearest Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, their great Possessions. They will forsake Father and Mother, Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that will not go out with them to meet the Bridegroom, and will follow him where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever he goes, as his Disciples did, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.27. So will the Virgins do, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1, 4. And it is the Duty of all Christs Disciples so to do, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26, 27. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.37, 38, 39.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45884:12"/> And they that forsake all their Relations, Estates, Lands, Houses, Goods and all for Christ, shall not lose by so doing, Luk. 18.28, 29, 30. &amp; Mark 10.28, 29, 30. Rev. 22.12. <hi>Behold I come quickly and my Reward is with me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Meditation.</hi> That such Gospel Light will be revealed to Virgin Professors in the later dayes, and such anointing of the Spirit will be poured out upon them, as will cause them and make them willing to sell all, lose all and forsake all, and go out to meet the Bridegroom.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Gospel Light touching the Kingdom and Coming of the spiritual Bridegroom our Lord Jesus Christ will be revealed in the later dayes, Matth. 24.14. <hi>And this Gospel of the Kingdom shall be Preached in all the world— And then shall the END come,</hi> Zech. 14.6, 7, 7. <hi>It shall come to pass, That at Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Time it shall be light. — And the Lord shall be King over all the Earth. In that DAY shall there be ONE Lord and his Name ONE.</hi> And Rev. 22.5. <hi>The Lord God giveth them Light— And they shall see his face, and his Name shall be in their foreheads, And they shall Reign for ever and ever— Which must shortly be done,</hi> Behold I come quickly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:45884:12"/>2. The Anointings of the Spirit, the Gifts and powerful operations of the Spirit will be upon Virgin Professors in the later Dayes, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28, 29. <hi>Isa.</hi> 43.3, 5, 6. <hi>&amp; Chap.</hi> 32.15, 16, 17. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.13, 14, 20, 27. The Fathers, the young Men, and the little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren shall have the <hi>Ʋnction</hi> of the Holy ONE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then it will be with Virgin Professors as it was in the Apostles Dayes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, <hi>&amp;c. There are Diversities of Gifts but the same spirit; and there are diversities of operations but the same God; All these worketh one and the self same Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. This Gospel Light, Anointing and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Holy Spirit upon Virgin Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors in the last Dayes will ingage them and make them willing to go out to meet the Bridegroom, Psal. 110.2, 3. <hi>The Lord will send the Rod of thy strength out of Sion: Rule thou in the midst of thine Enemies. Thy People shall be willing in the DAY of thy power, in the Beauties of Holiness,</hi> &amp;c. God will put his Spirit within them and cause them to walk in his wayes, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. HE will pour his Spirit upon them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.29. and they shall obey his voice, Matth. 25.6. <hi>Behold the Bridegroom cometh, go yet out to meet him.</hi> And they went out to meet the Bridegroom.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="verse">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45884:13"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Vers. 2.</hi>
                     </bibl> And five of them were wise and five were foolish.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>In this Parable Virgin Professors in the Churches of Saints are variously distinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Christ; viz. <hi>Five of them are wise and five are foolish.</hi> 2. The Foolish took no Oyle with them, but what was in their Lamps, <hi>vers.</hi> 3. The Wise took Oyle in their Vessels with their Lamps, <hi>vers.</hi> 4. 3. The Lamps of the Wise Virgins <hi>(being trimmed and supplyed with oyle in their Vessels)</hi> continued burning, The Lamps of the foolish Virgins <hi>(being trimmed but not supplyed with oyle)</hi> went out, <hi>vers.</hi> 7, 8. 4. The Wise Virgins, <hi>being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> went in with the Bridegroom to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: but the foolish Virgins, <hi>not being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared,</hi> were shut out, <hi>vers.</hi> 10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p>This verse contains the first <hi>Distinction</hi> of Virgin Professors; Five were wise, and five were foolish. Five is a <hi>definite</hi> number put for an <hi>indefinite,</hi> and thereby a small number is here put for a great number, and a few for very many, the five <hi>foolish</hi> Virgins, for all sorts of Gospel Professors, who having a form of Godliness want the power thereof, 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 3.5. And the five <hi>wise</hi> Virgins, for all sorts of Worshippers of God that make <hi>not only</hi> a Profession of Christ, but have <hi>also</hi> Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45884:13"/> of Christ dwelling in their hearts, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3.17. both which particulars will plainly appear in the Exposition and handling of the 3 and 4 verses.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meditation.</hi> There are some wise, and many foolish Virgins.</p>
               <p>The Holy Spirit hath given many distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishing Characters in the Scripture of Truth between these wise and foolish Virgins, whereof some in this Parable, which I have already mentioned in General, and shall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards shew particularly. And the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Distinctions between sanctified Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Hypocrites; between them, that <hi>only</hi> seem to be Religious, and them that are <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely</hi> so in deed and Truth; between those that are in Christ, having an Everlasting and unseparable Union with him, and those that are without Christ, who make a profession of Christ, but have not possession of Christ in their hearts; I say all those scripture distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are applicable, and may be accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated unto wise and foolish Professors, but especially that Scripture <hi>Distinction,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1-5. which the holy Spirit makes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>them that have the form, and them that have the power of Godliness,</hi> which Christ in this Parable doth metaphorically express by the foolish Virgins, <hi>vers.</hi> 3. who took their Lamps, but took no Oyle with them, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45884:14"/> the Wise Virgins, that took Oyle in their Vessels with their Lamps, <hi>vers.</hi> 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3, 4" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Vers. 3, 4.</hi>
                     </bibl> They that were foolish took their Lamps, and took no Oyle with them. But the wise took Oyle in their Vessels with their Lamps.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>By Lamps we are to understand Temple Light, <hi>viz.</hi> Divine knowledge and spiritual Gifts, as hath been proved in the Exposition of the <hi>first</hi> verse, Whereby our Saviour did Mystically and Metaphorically shew, <hi>That the foolish Virgins had a form of Godliness.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By Oyle in their Lamps is mean that shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning outward profession of Christ, which went out at last, vers. 8. <hi>Give us of your Oyle for our Lamps are gone out.</hi> The Light of the knowledge of Christ and of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and of the Mysteries of his Kingdom and Coming, which shined in the Profession they made, and in the Witness and Testimony that they had born for Christ against Antichrist, withered away and died; And all their common Gifts and Graces faded and failed; And they all fell away like the stony ground hearers, Luke 13.8. <hi>Who believe for a time, but in Time of Temptation fall away.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:45884:14"/>
               <p>By Oyle in the Wise Virgins Vessels we are to understand Jesus Christ, and the spirit of Christ and the sanctifying knowledge of Christ, and the saving grace of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ in their hearts and in their souls. For their souls are Vessels of Mercy prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for Glory, <hi>Rom</hi> 9.23, 24. And their My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical and spiritual Oyle is the Unction of the Holy ONE, which they have received, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.20, 27. Whereby our Saviour did figuratively and Mystically shew <hi>That the Wise Virgins had the power of Godliness.</hi> And in this part of the Parable of the Kingdom of Heaven, Christ declares and testifies, That they are foolish Virgins, who rest satisfied and content themselves with the form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness without the power of Godliness; who have Lamps but no Oyle.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That they are wise Virgins who have both Lamps and Oyle in their Vessels (<hi>to wit,</hi> Christ and his Spirit and his Grace in their hearts) having both the Form and Power of Godliness.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meditation.</hi> It's not the Lamp-light of Profession and the Form of Godliness; but the <hi>Oyle</hi> of Grace, and Sanctification, <hi>even</hi> the Power of Godliness in heart and Life, that will put the Denomination of, and distinction between wise and foolish Virgin Professors in the last dayes.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:45884:15"/>
               <p>Though this be very clear and plain b<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what hath been already said, in this Exposi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion; yet because I do think it may be profi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table, <hi>first,</hi> for the Conviction of some for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Professors, who are foolish Virgins, <hi>espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi> sinners in <hi>Sion,</hi> unconverted Church-members. And 2. For the Edification and Establishment of Sanctified Believers in the visible constituted Churches of Christ, <hi>espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi> weak Christians: I am therefore wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>(through Divine Assistance)</hi> to treat more largely of the Form and power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, (and therein to demonstrate the Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and folly of Virgin Professors) than I shall do of some other things held forth in this Parable, which I judge less necessary to inlarge upon.</p>
               <p>That which I shall offer to Consideration touching the Form and Power of Godliness doth consist in these three following Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>There is the Form of Godliness and the power of Godliness.</hi> All the Virgins had burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and shining Lamps, and some of them had Oyle in their Vessels with their Lamps, <hi>vers.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The form of Godliness may be where the Power of Godliness is not.</hi> The foolish Virgins took their Lamps, but took no Oyle with them, vers. 3. <hi>to wit</hi> in their Vessels, <hi>that is,</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:45884:15"/> They had the form of Godliness in their Profession, but they wanted the power of Godliness in their hearts and Conversation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>That some Virgin Professors in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Saints having the form of Godliness will deny the power thereof in the last dayes,</hi> of whom the Apostle spake expresly and foretold, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p>Touching the first Proposition, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies any form, or kind of Worship, or God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness; and having no Article joyned with it, it doth not signifie <hi>this, that,</hi> or <hi>the form</hi> of Godliness properly, or strictly; but indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely, any form, and every form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and consequently <hi>the form</hi> of Godliness.</p>
               <p>There are divers forms of Religion wherein men worship and serve God accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the different apprehensions and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasions of persons professing Godliness; whereof some, yea several are of mans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vising, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.8, 9. compared with <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20, 22, 23. But, there is a form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, which is of Gods own Institution un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Gospel, wherein Men ought to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God in Spirit and Truth, <hi>John</hi> 4.23, 24. according to his own appointments, <hi>Psal.</hi> 3.3.16.</p>
               <p>The Form of Godliness <hi>(of Gods own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment)</hi> consists in the External religious performance of all those Evangelical Duties
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45884:16"/> which he hath Commanded us in his holy Word, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.10, 11. according as he hath commanded, wherein persons seem to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Godly. Formal Professors do perform those religious Duties 1. From a principle of self which is the common and highest principle that formal Professors and Hypocrites are acted by in the Worship of God. They pray for themselves, fast and mourn for themselves and live to themselves, <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.4, 5, 6. Self-love, self-seeking, self-confidence, self-dependance, self-sufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, self-righteousness, and self-salvation is the frame and End of a formal professor. Self is the Spring and main principle of all he doth in his Religion, <hi>Hosea</hi> 10.1, 2. <hi>Israel</hi> is an empty Vine, He brings forth fruit unto himself.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From a principle of Tradition which they have received from their Fathers by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome and Education; So did the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> Worship God before his Conversion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing zealous of the Traditions of his Fathers, Gal. 1.14, 15. <hi>I profited in the Jews Religion above many— Being more exceedingly zealous of the Traditions of my Fathers.</hi> Thus many formal Professors now worship God after the Traditions and Customs of their Fathers and Teachers, as the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risees did, whom Christ reprehended <hi>Mark</hi> 7.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45884:16"/> 8, 9, 13. <hi>Ye hold the Tradition of men,</hi> and in vain did they worship God, making the word and Commandments of God of none effect by their Traditions. Jer. 7.18. &amp; 44.16, 17. <hi>The Children gather wood and the Fathers kindle the Fire, and the Women knead their Dough to make Cakes to the Queen of Heaven and to pour out drink offerings unto other Gods, that they may provoke me to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.—As for the word that thou hast spoken unto us in the Name of the Lord, we will not hearken unto thee —But we will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly do whatsoever thing goeth forth out of our own mouth to burn incense unto the Queen of Heaven, and to pour out drink-offerings un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, as we have done, we and our Fathers, our Kings and our Princes in the Cities of</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, <hi>and in the streets of</hi> Jerusalem: <hi>for then had we plenty of Victuals, and were well, and saw no evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. From a principle of fear; <hi>legal fear, (to wit,</hi> the fear of hell, wrath or Curse, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> causeth many professors, to pray, hear Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, perform holy duties, and to partake of Gods Ordinances; Also <hi>a servile fear</hi> of the Anger and displeasure of men, causeth many Children and Servants to Worship God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally, and they seem to be Religious because they are afraid to anger and displease their Godly Parents, Masters, or some other Godly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45884:17"/> Relations; And that their <hi>fear of God</hi> is taught by the Commandments of men, <hi>Isa.</hi> 29.13. And thereby they are made confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable unto the External parts of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and attain unto a Form of Godliness; yet are without the power thereof.</p>
               <p n="4">4. From a Principle of superstition many are like the Idolaters of <hi>Athens,</hi> who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped the unknown God, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.22, 23. they were very superstitious in their Will-worship of God. The Zeal and Superstition of the Scribes and Pharisees made them so formal in their legal Ceremonial worship of God, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.12. I fast <hi>twice a week,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.2. Many of the Jews being zealous in their Devotion, but wanting know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, worshipped God according to the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious Inventions of men, which things <hi>saith the Apostle</hi> have indeed a shew of wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in will-worship, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20, 23. And do make formal professors subject to ordinances of God after the Commandments and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of men.</p>
               <p>This may suffice to evince and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate <hi>That there is a form of Godliness.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed none can Externally worship God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out some form of Godliness, wherein Persons do seem to be Religious and may seem to be like God in Holiness and Righteousness both in Worship and Conversation in some measure.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:45884:17"/>
               <p>As there is the <hi>Form</hi> of Godliness, so there is the <hi>power</hi> of Godliness. The Power of Godliness consists, 1. In the truth of Grace. 2. In the lively Acts and Exercise of Grace. and 3. In the Growth and perfection of Grace.</p>
               <p>The power of Godliness consists <hi>first,</hi> in the truth of Grace. In whatsoever <hi>form</hi> of Religion any professors worship God; yea though that <hi>External</hi> form be ordained of God, instituted by Jesus Christ and practised by the Apostles, Churches and Saints; yet for all this without the Truth of Grace, they are void of the power of Godliness. And therefore the primitive Saints did not only receive the Ordinances but the Truth of Grace also by the Ministry of the Apostles in the Dispensation of the Gospel, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6, 7, 8. And knew the Grace of God in Truth.</p>
               <p>True Grace is the incorruptible seed of the New Birth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. and of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God in the hearts of Believers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.31, 32. which Kingdom of God within us, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.21. is not in Word only, but in power and in the holy Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.20. &amp; 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.4, 5.</p>
               <p>Now the Power of Godliness doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate it self by true saving sanctifying Grace, 1. In denying all ungodliness. 2. In
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45884:18"/> living soberly, righteously and Godly in this present evil World, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12. This is the constant frame of a Believers heart. He would not sin, he hates all sin; He would be holy, he loves holiness, and desires to be more holy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15, 16, 19, 20, 21, 22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The power of Godliness doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist in the lively Acts and Exercise of Grace; as the form of Godliness appears in the frequent Exercise of holy Duties, so doth the power of Godliness appear in the lively Acts and Exercise of holy Graces, <hi>to wit,</hi> in the life and lively work of faith, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.11, 12. Also in the labour of fervent love, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22. Bearing all things, enduring all things with all Brotherly kindness, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4, 7. &amp; <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10. Likewise in the constant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of Patience, humility, meekness, and self denyal, taking up the Cross daily, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it patiently, following the steps of Christ, who humbled himself unto death, even the Death of the Cross: Yea, and he endured the Cross. Now Believers who have the power of Godliness, are armed with the same mind, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1. and desire to be like minded to Christ, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5, 8. They suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer patiently, knowing that tribulation <hi>(which is the tryal of their faith)</hi> worketh patience, and are desirous that patience may have her perfect work <hi>James</hi> 1.2, 3, 4.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:45884:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Power of Godliness doth consist in the growth and perfection of grace, grace is of a growing nature, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. For 1. It grows in its Root which is Jesus Christ, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6, 7. As the good seed that is sown in good ground and brings forth fruit, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.8, 15. The Reason why meer formal Professors fall away is, because they are not rooted nor grafted into Christ, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.13. And the Reason why those Believers that are ingrafted into Christ, grow as <hi>Cedars</hi> in <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon,</hi> as a green <hi>Olive</hi> Tree in the House of the Lord, and bring forth fruit as the Vine, is because they are trees of Righteousness, the planting of the Lord, <hi>Isa.</hi> 61.3. which take Root downward into Christ, and so bring forth fruit upward by that sap and nourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which they receive from that spiritual Root, <hi>to wit,</hi> those Divine Influences of the Spirit of Grace that they are made partakers of by being ingrafted and rooted into Christ. This growth in Grace is very secret, hidden, not seen nor alwayes discerned, like the growth of Corn under ground, or of Trees in Winter, or of the Child in the Womb; yet it doth afterwards appear and is visible.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Grace grows in its lively acts and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise: As a Child after its natural birth grows in all parts and Members of the Body; so a Child of God being regenerated and born
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45884:19"/> again of the incorruptible seed of the Word, doth grow in Grace and in the knowledge of Jesus Christ by adding one Grace to another, unto faith, vertue; to vertue, knowledge, temperance, patience, Godliness, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5-11. This growth in Grace de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrates the power of Godliness: by this spiritual growth in Grace, the weak in faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1. become strong in faith, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.14. and little faith becomes great faith; like the grain of Mustard seed that becomes a great Tree, and very fruitful, whereunto Christ likened the Kingdom of his Grace within us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.31, 32. with <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.21.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Grace grows in its fruits unto perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and hereby is the power of Godliness de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrated, to wit in bringing forth much fruit, <hi>John</hi> 15.5, 8. <hi>viz.</hi> the fruits of the holy spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23. which are the fruits of Holiness and Righteousness unto Eternal Life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.22. Thus fruitful were the Saints in the Church of the Thessalonians, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.3. And the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted the primitive Saints to perfect Holiness in the fear of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. And the Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> exhorted the called ones of God to be holy in all manner of conversation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15, 16. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he knew that the power of Godliness consisted in the life of holiness and righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and is demonstrated in a holy Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:45884:19"/>
               <p>Thus it appears, That there is the form of Godliness and the power of Godliness, which is the first proposition. The second Proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is this,
<q>That the Form of Godliness may be where the Power of Godliness is not.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Simon Magus</hi> seemed to be religious, He believed and was baptized, and took up the form of Godliness, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.12. But for all this formality he had not the power of Godliness, for he was in the gall of Bitterness and bond of Iniquity, and his heart was not right with God, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.21.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> his wife were both Professors, and Church-members; they had taken upon them the Name of Christ and the form of Godliness, seemed to be very charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and pretended much Brotherly Love to the poor Saints, for they sold a Possession, and gave a part of the price thereof unto the poor, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.1, 2. and yet they were void of the power of Godliness.</p>
               <p>Professors that are proud, covetous, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal covenant-breakers, false accusers, inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, fierce, heady, high-minded, Lovers of pleasures more than Lovers of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them have a form of Godliness, but they have not the power of Godliness, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:45884:20"/>
               <p>When Professors and Church-Members are generally <hi>formal</hi> in the performance of the duties of Religion, very <hi>perfunctory</hi> and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficial in the Worship of God, or Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm neither hot nor cold, <hi>very indifferent</hi> whether they observe the Lords Day or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Day, or no day at all to the Lord, so whether they hear the Word Preached, pray in their Families or in their Closets, or pray not at all, whether they come to the Lords Table or stay away, it argues they are so far from having <hi>the power of Godliness,</hi> that they can <hi>scarcely</hi> be said to have <hi>the form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again when Professors and Members of Churches are very frequent and constant in Assembling themselves together to worship God, very zealous and precise in the External part of the Worship of God and seem to be very Conscientious and scrupulous in such things as appertain to the form of Godliness, asserting and contending that all things ought to be exactly done in the Church of God, according to the Rule of the written word of God, and yet walk very disorderly at home, are heady and unruly in their own houses, set no Rules nor Bounds to their obstinate and perverse Wills, to their inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate and vile affections, to their worldly and covetous hearts, who seem to be Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45884:20"/> yet bridle not their Tongues but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their own hearts; <hi>Their Religion is in vain,</hi> James 1.26. These Professors have a form of Godliness, but they want the power thereof.</p>
               <p>Thus it appears that the form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness may be where the power of Godliness is not. Professors may have Leaves without fruit, as the Fig-tree had; Lamps, and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but no Oyle in their Vessels, like the foolish Virgins; seem very Religious in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Saints, and be very irreligious in their Conversation among sinners.</p>
               <p>The Reasons why Professors rest in and hold up a form of Godliness without the power thereof are these. 1. Because they would have a name to live though they be dead, <hi>Rev</hi> 3.1. They are very desirous to have a Name in the house of God, to be accounted religious and to be numbred among the Saints; therefore they take up a form of Godliness and rest therein.</p>
               <p>Those foolish Professors, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.1, 2. had gotten a Name among the wise, and were called <hi>Virgins.</hi> And they seemed to be <hi>Religious:</hi> they had Lamps of Gospel Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, and the form of Godliness wherewith they were satisfied, and therein they rested securely till the Bridegroom came, and then
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45884:21"/> it appeared they wanted Oyle, that is, the truth of Grace and power of Godliness; for want whereof they were excluded and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by Jesus Christ, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.8, 11, 12.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Because a form of Godliness will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port with a spirit of Wordliness, Earthly-mindedness, Covetousness, Pride, Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, Drunkenness; so that these Lusts be but secretly committed. A Professor and Church-member may be a self-lover and a lover of pleasures, a Covenant or Promise-breaker, and yet have and hold up a form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness without the power thereof, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1-5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Because Professors and Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers may avoid troubles and persecutions, whilest they enjoy Sabbaths, Sermons, and Ordinances in an External form of publick Worship; Whereas the power of Godliness will expose them to suffer persecution, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. So that the Form of Godliness may be where the power is not. This is the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Proposition. There is a Third Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That some Professors and Church-members having and holding up the form of Godliness, deny the power thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Professors they must be and Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers they may be, that have and hold up the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45884:21"/> form of Godliness, and seem to be very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout and Religious in the Worship of God, and yet some of them deny the power of Godliness. We have shewed in the handling of the first proposition wherein the form of Godliness and wherein the power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness doth consist, and have treated briefly both of the form and power of Godliness. Now it remains, That in handling this Third Proposition, <hi>we shew,</hi> 1. <hi>what it is to deny the power of Godliness.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Reasons why they deny the Power of Godliness.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To deny the power of Godliness, is 1. To have an Aversation against it in their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not to love and affect the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness; which Aversation against the power of Godliness doth arise and spring from that cursed and sinful Enmity in their carnal minds against God, Rom. 8.7. <hi>The carnal mind is Enmity against God,</hi> and therefore carnal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors do not love nor like Godliness in the Truth and power of it, though they may be found in the form and profession thereof. O, saith a formal professor in his heart, I do not love this preciseness, this is to be righteous overmuch. I like not those that are so strict, so zealous and so scrupulously conscientious. What necessity is there to deny my self, my Liberty, my lawful Recreation, content and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45884:22"/> delight in things indifferent? must my liberty therein be judged by another Brothers or Sisters Conscience? He loves not, he likes not this, it crosseth his Interest in the World, or it is contrary unto some of his beloved and indulged Lusts to be so zealous, so Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, so Conscientious as the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness requireth, and would ingage him to be, therefore he is averse from it, and so may be said to deny it.</p>
               <p>To deny the power of Godliness, is 2. To Refuse all the offers of Christ and Grace, which God makes them in the ministry and administration of the Gospel by his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Isa. 53.1, 2, 3. Act. 3.13, 14. <hi>But ye denyed the Holy ONE.</hi> That is, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused Christ, and would not have him to be their Saviour, King, Priest and Prophet, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>We will not have this man to Reign over us.</hi> Formal Professors know not the worth of Christ, they are not sensible of their want of Grace, therefore they slight, neglect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse the Offers of Grace. They are willing to seem Religious, but as for the truth of Grace and power of Godliness they regard it not. They like Christ as a Saviour but refuse him as a Soveraign; though they would be saved, they care not to be sanctified; they refuse to enter in at the strait gate of Grace, and to walk in the narrow way of holiness,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:45884:22"/> and yet they would go to Heaven, and to that end they cry, Lord, Lord, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.21, 22. They pray and Prophesie in Christs name, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.23, 27. They worship God, seem to be very religious and partake of all Gods holy Ordinances, having a form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, but yet they deny the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness by refusing the offers of Christ and Grace in the Gospel and Ordinances of God.</p>
               <p>To deny the power of Godliness is, 3. To live in the practice of known sins, secretly indulging and allowing them, Tit. 1.16. <hi>They profess that they know God, but in Works they deny him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When Professors Lives are loose, carnal, worldly, and their works are the works of Darkness, and they themselves workers of Iniquity, they deny God and the power of Godliness.</p>
               <p>The power of Godliness consists in practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Holiness. Some Professors seem to be Holy in Gods house, who live very ungodly in their own houses. They seem to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious in the Church and in the Worship of God, but they are irreligious at home, in their Shops and Callings, Trading and Living in sin, and ungodliness. These having a form of Godliness deny the power thereof.</p>
               <p>Now the Reasons why <hi>Formal Professors deny the power of Godliness,</hi> are 1. Because
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:45884:23"/> their hearts are not right with God; <hi>Simon Magus</hi> Believed and was baptized, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped God, but his heart was not right with God, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.21, 23. There is a carnal Enmity in their hearts against God, and the power of Godliness; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. though they like the outward form, yet they love not the inward power of Godliness.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Because the inward power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is cross to their outward and worldly Interests, therefore they deny the power thereof. The Formalist saith within himself, though I be religious, a Church-member, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet I am resolved to make my Religion and Church-fellowship comport with my Interest in the world, and to be subservient unto my Honour, Credit, Profit, yea and my pleasure, delight and contentment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When formal Professors discern that the power of Godliness will not only check and curb their vile affections, perverse wills, and sinful desires, but also will mortifie, kill and destroy their Lusts and Corruptions, root and branch, then they refuse and deny the power of Godliness.</p>
               <p>Rather than the Formalist will hazard the loss of Life, Liberty or Estate, and expose himself to poverty, prison, banishment or death for his Religion, he will deny Christ, deny God and the power of Godliness.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:45884:23"/>3. Because the power of Godliness enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth professors to follow Holiness, and to deny all ungodliness, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12. Such Professors as have the form of Godliness only, are very apt to rest in the external part and performance of holy duties and sacred Ordinances without the injoyment of God and Jesus Christ. But the truth and Life of Grace and the power of Godliness will not suffer the soul to rest in duties and Ordinances without the injoyment of fellowship and Communion with God, therefore the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malist will not close with the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, but refuseth and denyeth it, because he is unwilling to leave his sins. I shall now make some application of what I have said touching the form and power of Godliness.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Ʋse</hi> of Instruction to Virgin Professors.</p>
               <p>There are three things necessary unto the <hi>form</hi> of Godliness, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The knowledge of the Revealed Will of God in his written Word touching Christs Institution of Gospel Ordinances, and his Constitution of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God therein, and thereby. How can any person worship God in spirit and truth (<hi>as true worshippers ought to do,</hi> Joh. 4.23, 24.) unless they understand and know the truth, revealed in the holy Scriptures?</p>
               <p>Ignorant persons are not capable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45884:24"/> the external part of the worship of God; for they do not know it. The Athenians wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped the unknown God, which the Apostle told them was their great superstition, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.22, 23. And our Saviour told the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> that the Samaritans worship they know not what, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.21, 22. So then knowledge is necessary unto the form of Godliness.</p>
               <p>Many persons think it is enough that their Ministers know how they ought to worship God, and so are willingly ignorant, whose fear towards God is taught by the precepts of men, and they willingly walk after the Commandment, <hi>Hos.</hi> 5.11. which formality of Conformity Christ reprehended, Matth. 15.9. <hi>In vain they do worship me teaching for Doctrine the Commandments of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. In the <hi>form</hi> of Godliness there must be a Conformity unto the Revealed Will of God in his Word, especially in the External part of the Instituted worship of God in the Gospel.</p>
               <p>Uniformity in Worship in any Nation or Congregation without Conformity unto the <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>Canon</hi> of the holy Scripture, is but superstition and a worshipping God after the Inventions and Traditions of men, which the Apostle reproved in the Colossians, and calls <hi>Will-worship,</hi> Col. 2.20, 21, 22, 23.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:45884:24"/>
               <p>The Temple, the Altar and they that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, <hi>(that is, the Church,</hi> the <hi>worship of God and the worshippers of God)</hi> are to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured by the Reed or Rod of the Sanctuary, that is, by the written word of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Moses</hi> was commanded to do all things according to the pattern that God shewed him in the Mount, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5. and the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was commanded to shew the House of Gods worship to the House of <hi>Israel</hi> and admonished them to measure the pattern, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.10.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the Form of Godliness there ought to be an Uniformity among all the Churches of God in every Nation, in every City and in every Village. All that worship God in one place, are to Worship him in one way, with one accord and with one shoulder. It was so in the Apostles dayes, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.4, 24. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Being of one accord, of one mind,</hi> Act. 4.32. And so it shall be in the last dayes, Jer. 32.36, 38, 39. <hi>And I will give them one heart, and one way that they may fear me, (i.e.)</hi> worship me, <hi>for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Uniformity was <hi>tacitly</hi> hinted by the Apostle, in reproving the Confusion that was in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.26, 33. <hi>for God is not the Author of Confusion but of Peace,</hi> As in all the Churches of Saints.</p>
               <p>Uniformity in Worship not after the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:45884:25"/> of men, but according to the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Word of God makes for Peace, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Edification in the Churches of Saints, and is a special means to avoid confusion and disorder in the Worship of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Ʋse</hi> of Conviction, 1. Of those foolish Virgin-professors who rest in the form of Godliness without the power of it. They may hereby be convinced, 1. That their hearts are not right with God, though they do <hi>materially</hi> that which is right in the sight of God; but are like <hi>Amaziah</hi> who <hi>did that which was right in the sight of the Lord, but not with a perfect heart,</hi> 2 Chron. 15.1, 2. And whosoever rests in a form of Godliness, without the power thereof, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth his own heart, and his Religion is in vain, <hi>James</hi> 1.26.</p>
               <p>Such may be convinced, 2. That in all their solemn appearings before God, and their approachings nigh unto him, their hearts are far from him, <hi>Isa.</hi> 29.13. and <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.8. And testifies that all their worship is in vain, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.8, 9. And they themselves Hypocrites, <hi>vers.</hi> 7. As the heart is, so is the Worshipper in the sight of God. If the heart be proud, covetous, vain, foolish, luke-warm, formal and hypocritical, all that Professors duties, performances and worship is abhorred
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:45884:25"/> of God, his soul hateth them. Isa. 1.12, 13, 14, 15. and Chap. 66. ver. 3. <hi>Bring no more vain oblations, incense is an abomination to me, the New Moons and Sabbaths, the calling of As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies, I cannot away with. It is iniquity, even the solemn meetings,—Your New Moons, and your appointed feasts my soul hateth, they are a trouble unto me, I am aweary to bear them.</hi> —And when ye <hi>spread forth your hands, I will hide mine Eyes from you; yea when you make many prayers, I will not hear: your hands are full of blood. He that killeth an Ox is as if he slew a man, he that sacrificeth a Lamb as if he cut off a dogs neck, he that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth an oblation as if he offered swines blood, he that burneth Incense as if he blessed an Idol; yea they have chosen their own wayes, and their soul delighteth in their Abominations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They may be convinced, 3. That they shall never see God in Heaven, Heb. 12.14. <hi>for without Holiness</hi> (the power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness) <hi>no man shall see the Lord.</hi> They are declared by God in his Word to be Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.7, 8, 9. and if they Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent not, they shall have their portion with Hypocrites, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.51. in the lowest and deepest of eternal flames, and of everlasting darkness, there shall be weeping and gnash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Teeth.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:45884:26"/>3. <hi>Ʋse</hi> of Consolation unto the Wise Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins. Art thou an Israelite indeed? Dost thou worship God in Spirit and Truth? Hast thou both the form and power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness? Then be of good Comfort. For, 1. Christ is thine, and all is thine, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21, 22, 23. God is thy Father, Grace is thy por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Heaven is thine Inheritance, Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is thy way, and Happiness will be thine end, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thou dost and shalt enjoy spiritual Communion with God in holy duties, and in his sacred Ordinances. The power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness doth make the Believer fruitful under that form of Godliness which Christ hath Instituted for the Worship of God; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords him fellowship with the Father, Son and Spirit, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Know for thy comfort, That the power of Sin, Satan, Hell cannot, shall not prevail against the power of Godliness in thee, so far as to provoke the Lord to forsake thee for ever, or to cause thee to forsake God for ever, for He hath said, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3, 5. I will never leave thee, never never forsake thee. Read for thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort Jer. 32.38, 40. <hi>And they shall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me.</hi> But the power of Godliness in thee will by the power of Christ prevail against, conquer and overcome the power of darkness, and all the wiles of the wicked one,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:45884:26"/> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.13. also the power of this world, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12, 13. and the threats, allurements, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thereof, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.4, 5. And likewise the power of sin, both the reigning power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (called the <hi>Dominion of sin</hi>) Rom. 6.14. sin shall not have Dominion over you, because ye are not under the Law, but under Grace; and the Tyrannizing power thereof (called the captivity of sin) Rom. 7.2, 3. &amp; 8.2. <hi>But the Law of the Spirit of Life in Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus hath made me free from the Law of sin and Death.</hi> Rejoice therefore in the Lord and bless him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5, 6, 8.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Ʋse</hi> of Exhortation, 1. To the Prophane. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. To Professors.</p>
               <p>And 3. To true Believers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A word to all prophane persons who have neither the power nor the form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness; I exhort such to consider their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful state and miserable condition, being all of them without Christ, having no hope, and without God in the World, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.12. <hi>David</hi> tells prophane sinners, The wicked shall be turned into hell, and all the People that forget God, <hi>Psal.</hi> 9.17. You can live without Christ, trade without Christ, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and give in marriage without Christ; But tell me, you prophane sinners, what will you do if you dye without Christ? can you think
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:45884:27"/> seriously of going to Hell, and being tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented there to Eternity? will the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the pleasures of sin for a season compensate the loss of your souls, and the pains of Hell for ever?</p>
               <p>Secondly, A word to the foolish Virgin Professors who having a form of Godliness deny the power thereof. I exhort such to consider seriously whether seeming to be Religious, and saying Lord, Lord, will save your immortal souls, Matth. 7.21, 22, 23. <hi>Not every one that saith unto me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, but he that doth the will of my Father which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven— Many will say to me in that Day, Lord, Lord, have we not prophesied in thy Name, and in thy Name have cast out Devils, and in thy Name done many wonderful works? — And then will I profess unto them, I never knew you, depart from me ye that work Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> Remember Professors that the foolish Virgins had their Lamps lighted, and they shined in the form of Godliness, but they found the Door of the Kingdom of Heaven shut against them. And when they said Lord, Lord, open to us, Christ said unto them, I know you not, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.10, 11, 12. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they had not the power of Godliness, Luk. 13.24, 28. <hi>Strive to enter in at the strait gate, for many I say unto you, will seek to enter
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45884:27"/> in, and shall not be able. — There shall be weeping and gnashing of Teeth, when ye shall see</hi> Abraham, Isaac <hi>and</hi> Jacob, <hi>and all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in the Kingdom of God, and you your selves shut out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do not rest in a form, without the power of Godliness, lest you sitting down in any Church of Saints and under the Sacred Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God without Christ, come short of Heaven, for without Holiness no man shall see the Lord, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God is not in word but in power, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.20.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, A Word to the wise Virgins that have not only the Form but the power of Godliness, whom I exhort, 1. To exercise the power of Godliness in the performance of holy Duties and in partaking of Gods holy Ordinances, and not to rest in the form and external part of the Worship of God. 2. To Demonstrate unto all that you have the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Godliness by being holy in all manner of Conversation, both in the house of God, and in your own houses, shewing forth the vertue of him that hath called you; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Faith, Humility, Self-denyal, Patience, the Love and Life of Jesus Christ may be manifested in your Life.</p>
               <div n="1" type="query">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:45884:28"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Querie 1.</hi> How may Professors attain unto the power of Godliness and so become wise Virgins.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sol.</hi> 1. Professors must come to Christ in the Ordinances of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18, 24. Christ complained of the Jewish Professors that they would not come to him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.40. many come to Sermons, to Duties, to Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but few come to Christ, most rest in the form without the power of Godliness, satisfying themselves in coming to Sermons, and attending upon Ordinances, without go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Christ in them, <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.3.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Gospel must come to professors not in word only, but also in power and in the holy Spirit, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.5. before they can come to Christ or attain to the power of Godliness.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Ministers of Christ must declare the Testimony of God not with excellency of speech, not with enticing words of Mans Wisdom, but their speech and their preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing must be in the Demonstration of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and in power, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.1, 2, 4, 5. before the Gospel can come to their hearers hearts in power and in the holy Spirit, and before their hearers can come to Christ, and before they can attain to the power of Godliness. The plain and powerful preaching of the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:45884:28"/> Gospel is the ordinary means whereby God draws sinners with Cords of Love to Christ, and makes the Ministry of the word power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and effectual to call, convert, sanctifie and save sinners, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14, 17.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Querie 2.</hi> How may Professors know, That they have attained unto the power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and that they are wise Virgins.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sol.</hi> Professors may know, That they have attained unto the power of Godliness, and are wise Virgins, 1. By the Victory they have obtained over the World, Satan, and their own sins. There's none but true Believers have overcome the world, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.4, 5. None but those that are strong in faith have overcome the Devil that wicked one, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.14. It's the truth of faith, and the power of Godliness, whereby sanctified persons do overcome their sinful Lusts and Corruptions; the Grace of God teacheth all men to deny ungodliness and worldly Lusts, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By the lively Acts and constant exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of Grace. In whomsoever the power of Godliness is, it will appear in the growth and exercise of Grace, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. Such Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians are fruitful under Gods holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:45884:29"/>
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5. The Gospel came to them not in word only but in power and in the holy Spirit, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.5. and their faith did grow exceedingly, and the Love of them all exceeded, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.3.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By their holy Conversation in the World, 2 Cor. 1.12. <hi>This is our Rejoycing, the Testimony of our Conscience that in simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and Godly sincerity by the grace of God we have our Conversation in the World.</hi> The power of Godliness will appear in a holy life and heavenly Conversation, as it did in the primitive Saints, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. whereunto they were exhorted, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15. <hi>viz.</hi> to be holy in all manner of Conversation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="query">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Querie 3.</hi> Are they, that have the power of Godliness, obliged to the form of Godliness?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sol.</hi> Yea, the Apostle commended the Church and Saints in <hi>Corinth</hi> for keeping the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1, 2. and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle <hi>Peter</hi> commanded them to be baptized with water, who had received the holy Spirit, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.47, 48. All the Apostles, the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Saints, and all true Believers looked at themselves to be obliged to the external form of Godliness and worship of God in external Gospel Ordinances, as it appears in the Acts of the Apostles and in their Epistles.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="verse">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:45884:29"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Vers. 5.</hi>
                        </bibl> While the Bride-groom tarried, they all slumbered and slept.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>The <hi>Bride-groom</hi> is the Lord Jesus Christ, <hi>vers.</hi> 1. who is here said <hi>to tarry</hi> or delay his coming, <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.48. which he will not do in respect of the time appointed of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Then he that shall come, will come, and will not tarry, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.37. But Christ is said to tarry or delay his coming;</p>
               <p n="1">1. Because He came not when they prayed for his coming, and earnestly desired his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence and appearance: thus Jesus tarried two dayes after <hi>Lazarus</hi> Sisters had sent him word that he was sick, <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.1, 3.6. and yet came in due time and manifested him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with power and great glory in raising <hi>Lazarus</hi> from the Dead, <hi>ver.</hi> 23.40, 43, 44.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Because He came not when they looked for him, and at the time when they expected his coming. The Apostle tells us, Heb. 9.28. <hi>Ʋnto them that look for him he shall appear the second time without sin unto Salvation.</hi> But of that day and hour knoweth no man, no not the Angels of Heaven, but my Father, said Christ, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.36.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They all slumbred and slept.</hi> All the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, both the foolish and the Wise Virgins.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:45884:30"/> First, They all slumbred or nodded, that is to say, they did not wake and watch as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they had done, while they waited for and expected the glorious appearance of their LORD, and bare their testimony of his coming; but began to be careless and secure, neglecting their Duty, they became drowsie and indisposed to wait any longer for the coming of the Bride-groom, grew weary, si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and sleepy as the Spouse did, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.16.5.1, 2. between her intreating and inviting her Beloved to come into his Garden, and his coming, <hi>I sleep but my heart waketh,</hi> ver. 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> They all slept, or were fast asleep, <hi>that is to say,</hi> the wise Virgins as well as the foolish were fallen into a state of security, <hi>as persons are when they are fast asleep in the night season,</hi> fearing neither Fire, thieves or any other danger. So all these ten Virgins <hi>(it being now near Mid night)</hi> were fast asleep <hi>(as it were in a dead sleep)</hi> through their carnal security, and careless neglect of their Watch and other Holy Duties. And some of them backslide into a deep Apostasie, and so continued till the Cry at Mid-night awaked them out of that deep sleep of carnal secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, backsliding and apostasie, into which they were fallen, as appears in the 6 and 7 verses of this Chapter.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:45884:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meditation.</hi> Many Virgin-professors being mistaken about this time of Christs coming, <hi>who tarried longer than they expected,</hi> will fall into the slumber of sinful silence and careless security. And some Professors will fall into a dead and deadly sleep of Backsliding and Apostasie. <hi>This Meditation consists of four Propositions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> Many Virgin-professors have been and are mistaken about this time of Christs coming. And that doth appear by what many learned and Godly men have written and witnessed touching the coming of Christ, <hi>many</hi> have looked for the coming of Christ, as the Judge of quick and dead, 2 Tim. 4.1. <hi>I charge thee therefore before God and the Lord Jesus Christ, who shall judge the quick and the dead at his appearing and his Kingdom.</hi> And that at the end of the World, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 10, 12. When he shall give up his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to the Father, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24-28. But few have expected the coming of Christ as the Bride-groom, and the <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> to come down from Heaven as a Bride adorned for her Husband, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1, 2. Who looks for the Marriage of the Lamb? and who will grant that his Bride shall make her self ready, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.7, 8. to be marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Christ and to live and reign with Christ a thousand years here on Earth between the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:45884:31"/>
                  <hi>final</hi> destruction of the Beast and the false Prophet and the Eternal Judgement of the last Day, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. But more will be spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the coming of Christ in the Exposition of the next verse.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Bride-groom tarryed longer than the Virgins expected, <hi>while the Bride-groom tarried,</hi> saith the Text; They expected his coming while they were awake, watching and witnessing, praying and looking for him, but He tarried till they all slumbred and slept. And then He came at Mid-night, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. at an hour (in a Dispensation) when they looked not for him. Matth. 24.44, 50. <hi>Therefore be ye also ready, for in such an hour as you think not, the Son of man cometh. —The Lord of that servant shall come in a day when he looketh not for him, and in an hour that he is not aware of.</hi> Matth. 25.13. <hi>Watch therefore for ye know neither the day nor the hour wherein the Son of Man cometh.</hi> And 1 Thes. 5.2. <hi>For your selves know perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the day of the Lord so cometh as a thief in the night.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The generality of Virgin-profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors will fall into the slumber of a sinful si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, neglect to watch and wait for the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Bride-groom; and grow careless and secure whilest he tarries.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:45884:31"/>
               <p>So long as Virgin-professors will be speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Christs Coming and Kingdom, and talking of his power (as was prophesied the later day Saints shall do, <hi>Psal.</hi> 145.11.) whilest they are praying continually for the coming and Kingdom of Christ (as He taught his Disciples to pray, Matth. 6.10. <hi>Thy Kingdom come:</hi>) And whilest they are watching and waiting for the Lord from Heaven in his glorious appearance with Kingly power and Majesty, as the Saints were exhorted by the Apostle to do, 1 Thes. 1.9, 10. <hi>To serve the living God and to wait for his Son from Heaven;</hi> I say, so long as Virgin-professors are so doing, they will not, cannot, shall not slumber nor sleep. But when they begin to be silent in bearing their Testimony for the Kingdom of Christ against the Kingdom of Antichrist, and will not, dare not speak of his glorious coming and Kingdom as the Bride-groom, but give over praying for it, and waiting for him; Then they begin to be careless of his coming, and to grow secure, <hi>and being at ease in Zion,</hi> begin to slumber, and at last some of them fall fast asleep.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Some Professors will fall into a deep and deadly sleep of Backsliding and Apostasie. As some of the later day Saints will be shining Believers, <hi>Isa.</hi> 60.1, 2. So
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:45884:32"/> some of the Virgin Professors in the last days will prove backsliding formalists and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Apostates, and this grand and greatest Apostasie hath these four steps or gradati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 1. A liberal inordinate resting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing their hearts in and upon worldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments. 2. A cooling in their Affections and careless neglect of holy duties, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and the pure worship of God. 3. A fearlesness of declining and backsliding. 4. A Benummed deadness, hardness, insensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleness, security and contentedness, being at ease and rest, and so fall asleep in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and this will happen a little before the coming of Christ, 2 Thes. 1.2, 3. <hi>Now we beseech you Brethren by the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, and by our gathering together in him — That ye be not soon shaken in mind, or be troubled, neither by spirit nor by word, nor by letters as from us, that the day of Christ is at hand — Let no man deceive you by any means, for that day shall not come exept there come a falling away first, and that man of sin be revealed, the son of perdition.</hi> This Apostasie was foretold also by the Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> in his second Epistle the third Chapter, and the 3 and 4 verses. <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this first, that there shall come in the last dayes Scoffers, walking after their own Lusts, and saying, Where is the promise of his coming;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:45884:32"/> for since the Fathers fell asleep all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue as they were from the beginning of the Creation.</hi> The Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> also foretold <hi>Timothy,</hi> that in the last dayes, <hi>(which will be perillous times)</hi> Men eminent for professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>(having the form of Godliness)</hi> will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the power thereof through their own Lusts, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. There are two Expressions used by both those Apostles touching this grand and last Apostasie which doth confirm my opinion, that they both prophesied and writ of the same Apostasie. <hi>Paul</hi> saith, 2 Tim. 3.1. <hi>This know also that in the last dayes.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> saith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Knowing that first —that in the later dayes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Root of this grand and last Apostasie is self-love, and love of pleasures, which the Apostle in his Epistle to <hi>Timothy</hi> notes to be the chief Character of the formal Professors and Apostates in the last dayes, 2 Tim. 3.2, 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The men of Name shall be <hi>Lovers of their own selves and Lovers of pleasures, more than Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of God.</hi> These sinful Pleasures, and worldly Contents cause Professors to slumber, and some to fall fast asleep in Apostasie, Self-love is that Root of bitterness out of which those unblessed, yea those cursed Branches of sinful lusts <hi>(there mentioned)</hi> do sprout and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:45884:33"/> grow, <hi>especially</hi> Covetousness, Pride and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-breaking. And the Love of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures is the corrupt fountain from whence the bitter waters of those sinful Lusts spring and flow.</p>
               <p>Let him that hath understanding judge what I say. If MEN not profane <hi>only</hi> but Professors <hi>also,</hi> not only the men of the world, but also members of Churches do love them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves more than truth and Righteousness, and love the world more than faith and a good Conscience, yea love their vain sinful delights and pleasures more than God and Jesus Christ, may not those and such as those be ranked and numbred among the Apostates and Backsliders of the last dayes? By how much the more we see and know men that have been very eminent in profession above many others, and have been highly esteemed in the Churches of Saints, <hi>men of name,</hi> Chief men among the Brethren, yea among the Elders for knowledge, Gifts, Zeal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who have born a glorious Testimony for Christ against Antichrist: But yet they have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>(through love of themselves and love of pleasures and other sinful Lusts)</hi> Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slided, Revolted and Apostatized from what they formerly practised and professed before many Witnesses; may we not conclude them to be among the number of the Apostates of the last dayes?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="verse">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:45884:33"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Vers. 6.</hi>
                     </bibl> And at midnight there was a cry made, Behold the Bride-groom com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, go ye out to meet him.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p n="1">1. Night doth Mystically and Metaphori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally signifie a time of Rest, Ease and Quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, also drowsiness, sluggishness, and a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing disposition; likewise a condition of a sinful careless security, Rom. 10.11, 12. <hi>And that knowing the time that now it is high time to awake out of sleep, for now is our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation nearer than when we believed— The Night is far spent, the day is at hand, let us therefore cast off the works of darkness, and let us put on the Armour of light.</hi>— 1 Thes. 5.2, 6, 7. <hi>For your selves know perfectly, that the day of the Lord cometh as a thief in the night— Therefore let us not sleep as do others, but let us watch and be sober— For they that sleep, sleep in the night, and they that are drunken are drunken in the night</hi>— Matth. 24.48, 49, 50. <hi>But and if that evil servant shall say in his heart, My Lord delayeth his coming, and shall begin to smite his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low servants, and to eat and drink with the drunken, The Lord of that servant shall come in a day when he looketh not for him and in an hour that he is not aware of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:45884:34"/>2. A condition and time of great dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, discomfort, sore Afflictions and heavy Judgements, Exod. 12.29. <hi>And it came to pass, That at Midnight the LORD smote all the first Born in the Land of Egypt:</hi> Mich. 3.6, 7. <hi>Therefore Night shall be unto you, that ye shall not have a Vision, and it shall be dark unto you that ye shall not divine, and the Sun shall go down over the Prophets and the day shall be dark over them— Then shall the Seers be ashamed, and the Diviners confounded, yea they shall cover their Lips, for there is no Answer of God.</hi> Joel 3.1. <hi>Gird your selves and lament ye Priests, howle ye Ministers of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar: come lye all night in sackcloth ye Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of my God; for the Meat-offering and the Drink-offering is withholden from the house of your God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. A time of greatest retirement and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose for most serious devotion and spiritual Meditation, and holy Contemplation, Psal. 4.4. <hi>Commune with your own heart upon your Bed, and be still,</hi> &amp;c. Psal. 16.7. <hi>My reins shall instruct me in the night season:</hi> Cant. 3.1. <hi>By night on my Bed I sought him whom my Soul loveth, I sought him but found him not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Midnight Dispensation in the text doth <hi>Mystically and Metaphorically</hi> signifie all these three particular conditions at the time of the <hi>Bridegroom's</hi> coming, with respect to the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:45884:34"/> several sorts of persons, who will be then and in that day concerned therein, <hi>viz. First,</hi> The foolish Virgins will then be found in a slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gish disposition and condition of a sinful care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less security, so sleepy that their Lamps go out, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. And the Wise Virgins will be too secure and careless at that time, <hi>ver.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Worldly Professors who are taught to Worship God according to the Commandments and precepts of men, and the Inventions and Superstitions of men will then be found under great darkness, discomfort and amazement, Luk. 21.25, 26, 27. <hi>And there shall be signs in the Sun, and in the Moon, and in the Stars, and upon the Earth distress of Nations with perplexity, the Sea and the Waves roaring—Mens hearts failing them for fear, and for looking after those things which are coming on the Earth, for the powers of Heaven shall be shaken— And then shall they see the Son of Man coming in a Cloud with power and great glory;</hi> Because of the sore Afflictions and Righteous Judgements of God, Matth. 24.21, 29, 30. <hi>For then shall be great tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. such as was not from the beginning of the World to this time, no nor ever shall be— Immediately after the tribulation of those dayes shall the Sun be darkened, and the Moon shall not give her light, and the Stars shall fall from Heaven, and the powers of the Heavens
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:45884:35"/> shall be shaken— And then shall appear the Sign of the Son of Man in Heaven, and they shall see the Son of Man coming in the Clouds of Heaven with power and great glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> There will be some, a few, a small Remnant of Virgin Saints who will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the Bridegroom when he comes, <hi>even in the midnight dispensation,</hi> and they are those hundred forty four thousand who have their Fathers name written in their foreheads, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. being in their retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, repose and secret devotion <hi>formerly</hi> sealed for the Servants of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.3, 4. And now come with the Bridegroom and shall stand with the Lamb upon Mount <hi>Sion</hi> being without fault before the Throne of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There was a Cry made,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Question is, 1. What <hi>Cry</hi> this was? 2. Who made this <hi>Cry?</hi> 3. Who heard this <hi>Cry?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the <hi>first</hi> Question, What Cry this was, I answer the Greek word (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) doth both here and in many other places of Scripture signifie a very loud, fierce and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Cry, as Act. 7.57. <hi>They cryed out with a loud voice,</hi> Act. 19.28. As an <hi>Herauld</hi> at Arms cries out with a loud voice when he proclaims an Edict, or when the common Cryer makes proclamation, Rev. 7.2. <hi>He cryed with a loud voice,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.17.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:45884:35"/>
               <p>Touching the second Question, <hi>Who made this Cry,</hi> I answer, either the LORD himself, or the Ministers of Christ, or the people of God.</p>
               <p>For this <hi>Cry</hi> is <hi>either</hi> by Preaching the coming of Christ publickly, Isa. 58.1. <hi>Cry aloud, spare not, lift up thy voice like a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.14. And the Gospel of the Kingdom (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) shall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed or preached publickly (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) in all the inhabited world, or else a Cry raised by the voice of a great number of the Saints and Servants of God in the Temple of God that was opened in Heaven, Isa. 66.6. <hi>A voice of the LORD a voice from the Temple,</hi> after the Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the two prophetical Witnesses of Christ which the Beast had killed, compare Rev. 11.7, 11, 12, 17, 19. <hi>And they heard a great voice from Heaven, saying unto them, come up hither,</hi> ver. 12. with Rev. 19.1, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>And a voice came out of the Throne, and I heard as it were the voice of a great multitude, saying</hi> Alleluja, <hi>for the Lord God omnipotent reigneth. Let us be glad and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and give honour to him, for the Marriage of the Lamb is come. Blessed are they that are called to the Marriage Supper of the Lamb. These are the true sayings of God,</hi> or by the Lord himself, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.16. Jehovah <hi>also shall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:45884:36"/> roar out of Zion, and utter his voice from Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem, and the Heaven and the Earth shall shake,</hi> read Hag. 2.6, 7. and Heb. 12.26, 27. and ver. 25. <hi>see that ye refuse not him that speaketh from Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the <hi>third</hi> Question, <hi>Who heard the Cry?</hi> I Answer, All the Virgins both wise and foolish heard this Cry, <hi>The Bridegroom cometh, go ye out to meet him,</hi> as appears in the next <hi>verse.</hi> For they all (being <hi>awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> by that loud Cry) rose and trimmed their Lamps, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. and <hi>probably</hi> there were many others, even great multitudes that heard this Cry or Proclamation of the Bridegrooms coming, who were glad and rejoyced that the Marriage of the Lamb was come, and that doth appear by what is prophesied and recorded <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.1. to the 9 <hi>verse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The sum and substance of this Cry is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in these words, <hi>Behold the Bridegroom cometh, go ye out to meet him,</hi> Wherein are three things to be observed, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The Attention, <hi>Behold.</hi> 2. The Assertion, <hi>The Bridegroom cometh.</hi> 3. The Obligation or Duty Enjoyned and Commanded, <hi>Go ye out to meet him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When God would have some wonderful and glorious thing made known unto the world and unto his people, He stirs up their Attention by this word, <hi>Behold, Isa.</hi> 65.1.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:45884:36"/>
                  <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.5. especially when God speaks of his Son Jesus Christ, <hi>Isa.</hi> 28.16. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.29. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7, 16.15.22.7. <hi>Behold he cometh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Behold I come quickly.</hi> So in the text, <hi>Behold the Bridegroom cometh.</hi> This is a matter which is worthy of, and calls for the Churches, Ministers and Saints Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Bridegoom cometh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It's not said HE will come, though that is true, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.37. Yet a little while and <hi>HE that shall come, will come, and will not tarry.</hi> But HE cometh (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) HE is upon his March, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, 12, 13, 14, 15. HE hath been coming a great while, HE went forth long ago, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.2. and now He is very near even at the Door ready to enter into the Bride-chamber; Only HE stands and stayes at the Door till the Bride have made her self ready, Rev. 19.7, 8. ver. 10. of this Chapter, <hi>And they that were ready went in with him to the Marriage and the Door was shut.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing that many both Learned and Godly men have been mistaken in their Opinions about the coming of Christ as was hinted in the Exposition of the former Verse; It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Churches of Saints, the Ministers of Christ, and all <hi>sanctified</hi> Believers to search
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:45884:37"/> the holy Scriptures and pray that God will by his holy Spirit open the Scriptures to us, and open our understanding thereby in this his coming.</p>
               <p>And now let not the Churches Ministers, nor any of the Saints be offended with me for shewing my Opinion, touching this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Christ and the Scripture grounds and Reasons for the same, which I humbly offer with all submission unto their Judgement.</p>
               <p>I do believe and am perswaded that the coming of Christ (spoken of in this Parable, <hi>ver.</hi> 6.10.) is not the coming of Christ in his own person upon the Earth (though I do believe Christ will come the second time in his own person upon the Earth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.4, 5.) but this is his virtual, spiritual, powerful and glorious coming in his Saints and Sanction <hi>as the Bridegroom of his Church, the new Jerusalem, who shall also come down from God out of Heaven, prepared as a Bride adorned for her husband.</hi> Our <hi>Davids</hi> Mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Kingdom on Earth among his Saints, when HE shall be King of all the Earth, and all the Kingdoms of this world shall be Christs. And when the Lords redeemed Ones, whom HE hath made Kings and Priests to God, shall have the Kingdom and Dominion under the whole Heaven given to them, and they shall reign on Earth.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:45884:37"/>
               <p>And the reasons grounded on Srcipture are as followeth. 1. Negatively. 2. Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.</p>
               <p>Negatively, That the coming of Christ spoken of in the 6 &amp; 10 verses of this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is not the coming of Christ in his own person upon the Earth. <hi>First,</hi> Because at the personal coming of Christ on Earth, (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his appearing the <hi>Second</hi> time, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28.) all his Saints shall come with him, Zach. 14.5. <hi>And Jehovah my God shall come and all the Saints with thee,</hi> 1 Thes. 3.13. At the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ with all <hi>his Saints.</hi> The living Bodies of the Saints shall be changed and glorified. And the Bodies of the Saints deceased shall then be raised and also glorified, Phil. 3.20, 21. <hi>For our Conversation is in Heaven, from whence also we look for the Saviour our Lord Jesus Christ— who shall change our vile body that it may be fashioned like unto his glorious body, according to the working whereby he is able even to subdue all things unto himself.</hi> 1 Thes. 4.14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>For if we believe, That Jesus died and rose again, even so them also which sleep in Jesus will God hring with him. For this we say unto you by the word of the Lord, that we which are alive and remain unto the coming of the Lord shall not prevent them which are asleep— For the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:45884:38"/> shall descend from Heaven with a shout with the voice of the Arch-angel and with the Trump of God, and the dead in Christ shall rise first— Then we which are alive and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main shall be caught up together with them in the Clouds to meet the Lord in the Aire, and so shall we ever be with the Lord.</hi> But there will not be such a general and Physical Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection at the coming of Christ as the Bride-groom, for then the living Saints <hi>only</hi> shall enter into the Bride-Chamber, and those wise Virgins who never came personally into the Kingdom of the Father in Heaven shall be admitted into the Kingdom of the Son on Earth, Rev. 3.21. <hi>To him that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh will I grant to sit with me in my Throne; Even as I also overcame and am set down with my Father in his Throne,</hi> which Christ himself expounds, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26 saying, <hi>To him will I give power over the Nations,</hi> Even as <hi>(or the same power that) I received of the Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Because at the personal coming of Christ on Earth, will be the Universal <hi>Physical</hi> Resurrection of all that are dead (and the Physical change of all their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies that are then alive, 1 Cor. 15.51, 52. <hi>Behold I shew you a Mysterie we shall not all sleep,</hi> but we <hi>shall all be changed in a moment in the twinkling of an Eye at the last Trump
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:45884:38"/> (for the Trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised incorruptible and we shall be changed.)</hi> Which Resurrection Christ in <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.39, 40, 44. three times together testifies shall be <hi>at the last day,</hi> and Matth. 25.31, 32. <hi>When the Son of man shall come in his glory and all the holy Angels with him, then shall he sit upon the Throne of his Glory,</hi> compared with Rev. 20.11, 12, 13. <hi>And I saw a great white throne and him that sate on it, from whose face the Earth and the Heaven fled away, and there was found no more place for them. And I saw the dead small and great stand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and the Books were opened, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Book was opened which is the Book of life, and the dead were judged out of those things which were written in the Book according to their works — And the Sea gave up the dead which were in it, and death and hell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up the dead which were in them, and they were judged every man according to his Works:</hi> together with the eternal Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.33, 34, 46. 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9, 10. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Jude</hi> 14, 15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Because when Christ comes vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually and spiritually as the Bridegroom, then will begin the times of the Restituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all things. Then God will restore our Judges as at the first, and our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellours
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:45884:39"/> as at the beginning, <hi>Isa.</hi> 1.25, 26, 27. Then Christ will restore <hi>Israel,</hi> and restore the Kingdom to <hi>Israel, Mich.</hi> 4.7, 8. Even the first <hi>Dominion</hi> shall come to the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Zion, the Kingdom shall come to the Daughter of Jerusalem.</hi> Then Christ will make all things new, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. But when Christ shall come personally upon the Earth, <hi>(as the judge of quick and dead)</hi> then will be the dissolution of the material Heavens and Earth, and the <hi>final</hi> Consumption and Conflagration of all things, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4, 7, 12. <hi>When the Heavens being on fire shall be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved.</hi> Now consider that this great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation of all things, yea of the <hi>material</hi> Heavens and Earth <hi>(which the Scripture testifies will be at Christs, second coming,)</hi> cannot be at the beginning of his Kingdom here on Earth for above a thousand years, after that time <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> will be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together and compass the Camp of the Saints about and the beloved City, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 5, 7, 8, 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Objection.</hi> Doth not this Opinion exempt and exclude Christ from Rule and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty in his <hi>Monarchical</hi> Kingdom on Earth, contrary to Rev. 20.4. <hi>They lived and reigned with Christ a thousand years?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answer.</hi> No. Consider <hi>first,</hi> Christ may be said to be with a person or people, and they
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:45884:39"/> with him <hi>virtually</hi> by his Spirit and power or his powerful <hi>spiritual</hi> presence. <hi>Isa.</hi> 57.15. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Colos.</hi> 2.12, 13. As it is said, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Is not the LORD in Zion? Is not her King in Her?</hi> though not personally, but spiritually.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> As Christ is said to be in his <hi>Mystical</hi> Kingdom <hi>the Church of God here on Earth;</hi> where his Laws, his Statutes and his Ordinances are dispensed in his Name, and by the power of his holy Spirit: so will he be in his <hi>Monarchical Kingdom, the throne of his Father</hi> David <hi>here on Earth,</hi> Luke 1.32, 33. <hi>And the Lord God shall give unto him the Throne of his Father</hi> David. <hi>And he shall reign over the House of</hi> Jacob <hi>for ever, and of his Kingdom there shall be no end;</hi> not personally <hi>at the beginning of it,</hi> but vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually by his Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Did not the <hi>Caesars</hi> and Roman Senate go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the World by their Laws and Edicts, and by those Kings and Governours of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces whom they Commissioned and made Rulers for them? Is not the King of <hi>Spain</hi> said to Rule and Reign in those parts of <hi>America,</hi> and in other parts of the World, <hi>(which he or his Ancestors Conquered)</hi> by his Laws Civil and Ecclesiastical, although he himself was never present there in his own person? And doth not the Pope reign over
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:45884:40"/> the Kings and Kingdoms of the Earth, who have agreed and given their Kingdom to the Beast, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.17, 18. though he was never personally in those Kingdoms, but gives Commissions to his Kings, his Nuntio's, his Cardinals, and his Prelates to rule in his Name and by his Laws and Edicts, Canons and Constitutions to govern the people in those his Kingdoms?</p>
               <p>So shall Christ reign over all the Nations and Kingdoms of the World <hi>whom he shall Conquer,</hi> and they shall become his. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.5. And HE shall be King of all the Earth, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.9. And God shall give him the Throne of his Father <hi>David, Luk.</hi> 1.32.33. And the Judgement shall be given to the Saints of the most high, and they shall possess the Kingdom, and govern the Nations by Christs Laws, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14, 21, 27. and in his Name, and by his Commission with his holy Spirit and power, and in great glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Isa. 60.1, 2, 3, 7, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>Arise, shine, for thy Light is come and the glory of the Lord is risen upon thee— The Sons also of them that afflicted thee shall come bending unto thee, and all they that despised thee, shall bow themselves down at the soles of thy feet, and they shall call thee the City of the LORD, the</hi> Zion <hi>of the holy one of</hi> Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el— <hi>Whereas thou hast been forsaken
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:45884:40"/> and hated, so that no man went through thee, I will make thee an eternal Excellency and Joy of many Generations:</hi> from the beginning of the thousand years Reign, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. until the end thereof, which is Christs <hi>Davidical</hi> and <hi>Monarchical</hi> Kingdom. And after that Christ hath put down all Rule, all Authority and all power that are his Enemies, by the hands of his Saints, who shall bind Kings in Chains and Nobles in Fetters of Iron, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Judgement written, <hi>This honour have all the Saints,</hi> Psal. 149.7, 8, 9. Then will the Lord Jesus Christ himself come in his own person, and all his holy Angels and Saints shall attend him, Matth. 25.31, 32. <hi>When the Son of Man shall come in his glory and all the Holy Angels with him, then shall he sit upon the Throne of his glory— And before him shall be gathered all Nations, and he shall separate them one from another, as a Shepheard divideth his Sheep from the Goats.</hi> Then shall he sit upon the Throne of his Glory, and the Saints shall sit upon Thrones with Christ, Matth. 19.28. <hi>And Jesus said unto them, Verily I say unto you, that ye which have followed me in the Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, when the Son of Man shall sit on the Throne of his Glory: Ye also shall sit upon twelve Thrones, judging the twelve Tribes of</hi> Israel. Rev. 3.21. <hi>To him that overcometh
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:45884:41"/> will I grant to sit with me in my Throne, even also as I overcame and am set down with my Father in his Throne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This personal coming of Christ had its typical vision and mystical appearance at his Transfiguration, Matth. 17.1, 2, 9. <hi>And after six dayes Jesus taketh</hi> Peter, James <hi>and</hi> John <hi>his Brethren, and bringeth them up into an high Mountain, and was transfigured before them, and his face did shine as the Sun, and his raiment was white as the Light. And as they came down from the Mountain, Jesus charged them saying, Tell the Vision to no man until the Son of Man rise again from the dead.</hi> Those Apostles <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> his Brother, were they of whom Christ spake, Matth. 16.27, 28. <hi>For the Son of Man shall come in the Glory of his Father, with his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and then he shall reward every man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his works — Verily I say unto you, there be some standing here which shall not taste of Death till they see the Son of Man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Kingdom.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> being one of those three, bare his Testimony and Record thereof, 2 Pet. 1.16, 17, 18. <hi>For we have not followed cunningly devised Fables, when we made known unto you the power and coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, but were Eye-witnesses of his Majesty. For he received from God the Father honour and glory, when there came such
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:45884:41"/> a voice to him from the excellent glory, This is my Beloved Son in whom I am well pleased — And this Voice which came from Heaven we heard when we were with him in the holy Mount.</hi> And it shall be <hi>visible</hi> indeed, Mat. 24.27. For as the Lightning cometh out of the East, and shineth even unto the West, so shall also the coming of the Son of Man be, Acts 1.11. <hi>He shall so come</hi> in like manner as ye have seen him go into Heaven. And <hi>very glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious;</hi> For Christ shall come in the Glory of his Father, <hi>Mark</hi> 8.38. In his own glory, and his Fathers, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.26. In the glory of the holy Angels also, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.31. and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in the glory of all his Saints, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9, 10.</p>
               <p>Then shall Christ the King of Saints, the King of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the King of Nations be admired of all them that believe, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.10. <hi>and praised, saying, Who would not fear Thee O King of Nations,</hi> Jer. 10.7, 10. <hi>The Blessed and only Potentate, the KING of Kings and LORD of Lords,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.15. Then also shall the Saints be glorified, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20, 21. <hi>For, our Conversation is in Heaven, from whence we look for the Saviour, the Lord Jesus Christ — Who shall change our vile body, that it may be fashioned like unto his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Body,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Joh. 3.2. <hi>Behold now we are the Sons of God, and it doth not appear what
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:45884:42"/> we shall be, but we know that when he shall appear, we shall be like him, for we shall see him as he is:</hi> and Rewarded, Rev. 22.12. <hi>Behold I come quickly, and my reward is with me,</hi> Matth. 25.34. <hi>Come ye blessed of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, receive the Kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then wicked men and wicked Angels shall by Christ and his Saints be judged according to their Deeds, 1 Cor. 6.2. <hi>Do ye not know that the Saints shall judge the World?</hi> ver. 3. <hi>Know ye not that we shall judge Angels?</hi> and 2 Tim. 4.1. <hi>I charge you therefore before God and the Lord Jesus Christ who shall judge the quick and the dead at his appearing, and his Kingdom.</hi> And then shall Christ deliver up the Kingdom to God the Father, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24, 28. That as Christ is now All and in All <hi>Col.</hi> 3.11. so God the Father then shall be All in All, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28. Thus much Negatively.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Affirmatively.</hi> That the coming of Christ in the 6 and 10 verses of this <hi>Chapter</hi> is his virtual, spiritual, powerful and glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in his Saints and Sanction <hi>(As the Bridegroom of his Church the New Jerusalem, the holy City, the general Assembly and Church of the first born, written in Heaven, who also shall come down from God out of Heaven prepared as a Bride adorned for her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band)</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:45884:42"/> and in his Davidical Kingdom on Earth.</p>
               <p>For proof of this my opinion, search those places of holy Scripture, <hi>Isa.</hi> 60.2, 3, 7, 13. <hi>Psal.</hi> 110.1, 3. 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Arise, shine, for thy light is come, and the Glory of the Lord is risen upon thee. — For behold darkness shall cover the Earth and gross darkness the people: but the LORD shall arise upon thee and his glory shall be seen upon thee — And the Gentiles shall come to thy light, and Kings to the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of thy rising — All the flocks of</hi> Kedar <hi>shall be gathered together unto thee, the Rams of</hi> Nebajoth <hi>shall minister unto thee, they shall come up with acceptance on mine Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, And I will beautifie the house of my glory; the Glory of Lebanon shall come unto thee, the fir-tree, the pine-tree and the Box to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to beautifie the place of my Sanctuary, and I will make the place of my feet glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. The LORD said unto my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand, until I make thine Enemies thy footstool. Thy People shall be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the day of thy power, in the Beauties of holiness from the Womb of the morning, thou hast the dew of thy youth— When he shall come to be glorified in his Father, and to be admired in all them that believe (because our
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:45884:43"/> testimony among you was believed) in that day— And I looked and loe a Lamb on the Mount</hi> Sion, <hi>and with him an hundred Forty four thousand having his Fathers Name written in their foreheads — And I heard a voice from Heaven as the voice of many waters, and as the voice of a great thunder; and I heard the voice of harpers, harping with their harps. And they sung as it were a new Song before the Throne, and before the four Beasts, and the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and no man could learn that song but the hundred and forty and four thousand which were redeemed from the earth. These are they which are not defiled with Women, for they are Virgins. These are they which follow the Lamb whithersoever he goeth. These were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from among men, being the first fruits unto God, and to the Lamb. And in their mouth was found no guile, for they are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fault before the Throne of God. To the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Assembly and Church of the first Born which are written in Heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the Spirits of just men made perfect. And I saw a new Heaven, and a new Earth, for the first Heaven, and the first Earth passed away, and there was no more Sea. And I</hi> John <hi>saw the holy City New</hi> Jerusalem <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down from God out of Heaven prepared as a Bride adorned for her Husband. And I heard a great Voice out of Heaven, saying, Behold
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:45884:43"/> the Tabernacle of God is with men, and he will dwell with them, and they shall be his people, and God himself shall be with them and be their God. And God shall wipe away all tears from their eyes, and there shall be no more death, neither sorrow nor crying, neither shall there be any more pain, for the former things are passed away. And he that sate upon the Throne said, Behold I make all things new, And he said unto me write, for these words are true and faithful.</hi> Read <hi>Isa.</hi> chapt. 62. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly <hi>ver.</hi> 5. Christ <hi>not in his own person, but by his substitutes,</hi> doth marry his Church, <hi>so shall thy sons marry thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Go ye out to meet Him.</hi> The Virgins went out before and that of their own accord, and very early too; But now they are called out, and that by a loud voice, and are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>Go ye out to meet him.</hi> They who at <hi>first</hi> were so forward, are now at last so backward, that they must be provoked, stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up, yea rouzed out of their slumbering, sleepy, careless security, and commanded <hi>if not compelled</hi> to go out <hi>again</hi> to meet the Bridegroom.</p>
               <p>The Spouse of Christ said within her self, Cant. 3.2. <hi>I will rise now, I will seek him whom my soul loveth.</hi> And she said to her Beloved, <hi>Come my Beloved, Let us go up early to the Vineyards, there will I give thee my Loves,</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:45884:44"/> Cant. 7.11, 12. But for all this her ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, she cooled in her spiritual Affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Christ, was sleepy and indisposed for spiritual communion with her Beloved, she framed excuses, being lazy and loth to open the door, though she heard him call her, and knew his voice, Cant. 5.2, 3. <hi>I sleep but my heart waketh, it is the voice of my beloved that knocketh, saying, Open to me my Sister, my Love, my Dove, my Ʋndefiled, for my head is filled with the dew, and my Locks with the drops of the night. And I have put off my Coat how shall I put it on, I have washed my feet how shall I defile them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It hath been hinted in the Exposition of the first verse, in what respects the Virgins went out at first to meet the Bridegroom.</p>
               <p>Let us consider what is further intended and here Commanded them in these words, <hi>Go ye out to meet him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By going out <hi>again</hi> to meet the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, we may <hi>here</hi> understand three things, 1. A Rising and shaking off all security, carelesness and indisposition, to watch and wait for the appearance of Christ, Rom. 13.11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>And that knowing the time that now is, it is high time to awake out of sleep, for now is our salvation nearer than when we Believed — The night is far spent, the day is at hand, Let us therefore
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:45884:44"/> cast off the works of darkness, and let us put on the whole armour of God. Let us walk ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly as in the day, not in rioting and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenness, in chambering and wantonness, not in strife and envying. But put ye on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make no provision for the flesh to fulfil the Lust thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. A recovering themselves out of their Backsliding and Apostatizing condition, by Prayer, Repentance and Reformation, Jer. 3.12, 13, 14, 22. <hi>Go and proclaim these words towards the North and say, Return thou backsliding</hi> Israel, <hi>saith the Lord, I will not cause mine anger to fall upon you, for I am merciful saith the LORD, and I will not keep anger for ever. — Only acknowledge thou thine Iniquity, that thou hast transgressed against the LORD thy God, and hast scattered thy wayes to the strangers under every green tree, and ye have not obeyed my voice saith the LORD. Turn O back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sliding Children saith the LORD, for I am married unto you, and I will take you one of a City, and two of a Family, and I will bring you to</hi> Zion. — <hi>Return ye Backsliding Children, and I will heal your Backslidings. Behold we come unto thee, for thou art the LORD our God,</hi> Hos. 14.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. Read the whole Chapter.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:45884:45"/>3. A preparing to meet the Lord, Amos 4.12. 2 Chron. 30.19. <hi>Prepare to meet thy God O Israel. — That prepareth his heart to seek God the LORD God of his Fathers, though he be not cleansed according to the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification of his Sanctuary.</hi> Luk. 1.17. <hi>To make ready a people prepared for the Lord.</hi> So did those Virgins, the foolish seemingly, the wise sincerely, <hi>vers.</hi> 7. <hi>Then all those Virgins arose and trimmed their Lamps.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Meditation.</hi> There will be a Midnight Dispensation of Mystical and Spiritual dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness upon Professors, Isa. 60.2. <hi>Darkness shall cover the Earth and gross darkness the people,</hi> &amp;c. Distress and perplexity, and great Tribulation upon the Inhabitants of the Earth, Luk. 21.25, 26, 27. <hi>There shall be upon the Earth distress of Nations with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity; Mens hearts failing them for fear,</hi> &amp;c. Matth. 24.21, 29. And too great se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, formality and drowsiness upon some of the wife Virgins, sanctified Believers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the coming of the Lord Jesus in his Kingdom here on Earth, Matth. 26.40. <hi>What, could you not watch with me one hour?</hi> 41. <hi>Watch and pray,</hi> &amp;c. Rev. 3.3. <hi>If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou shalt not watch, I will come on thee as a thief, and thou shalt not know what hour I will come upon thee.</hi> Cant. 5.2, 3. <hi>I have put off my Coat how shall I put it on,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:45884:45"/> Matth. 24.37, 38, 39. &amp; Luk. 17.26, 30. <hi>As it was in the dayes of</hi> Noah <hi>and</hi> Lot, <hi>so shall it be in the dayes of the Son of Man. So shall also the coming of the Son of Man be. Even thus it shall be in the day when the Son of Man is revealed,</hi> Luk. 17.30.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Meditation.</hi> That there will be such a <hi>voice</hi> of the LORD, such a voice from the City, and from the Temple, such a loud Cry in the Time of the Midnight Dispensation, that will awake and rouze up all the slum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering and sleeping Virgins, Isa. 66.6. <hi>A voice of noise from the City, a voice from the Temple, a voice of the LORD that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth recompence to his Enemies,</hi> Rev. 11.12. And they (the slain or despirited Witnesses, ver. 7.) <hi>heard a great voice from Heaven, saying, Come up hither,</hi> Joel 3.6. <hi>Jehovah al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so shall roar out of</hi> Sion, <hi>and utter his voice from</hi> Jerusalem.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Meditation.</hi> That the next glorious appearance of the Lord Jesus Christ will be his virtual and spiritual coming in his Saints and Sanction (as the Bridegroom <hi>of his Church</hi>) to marry her by her Sons, <hi>Isa.</hi> 62.4, 5. and by them to reign over the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with power and great glory a thousand years here on Earth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27.</p>
               <p>There are but three <hi>special</hi> kinds and times of Christs coming. 1. His coming in the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:45884:46"/> form of a servant in the dayes of his flesh, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7. 2. His coming as a Judge at the last day, when he shall judge the quick and the dead, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. called his appearing the second time, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. Both these are his personal appearances or his coming in his own person. But between these two ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances or comings of Christ in his own person, there is witnessed by the Holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apostles, and recorded in the holy Scripture of truth, another <hi>kind</hi> of Christs coming at <hi>another</hi> time. And that is his coming as the Bridegroom, and as the only Potentate, King of Kings and Lord of Lords, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.14, 15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.16. which is his virtual, spiritual, powerful and glorious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Saints and Sanction, and by them to marry his <hi>Jerusalem, Isa.</hi> 62.4, 5. so shall thy sons marry thee, and with them to reign over the Nations and Kingdoms of the World, a thousand years on Earth, Rev. 11.15, 16, 17. <hi>And the seventh Angel sounded, and there were great voices in Heaven, saying, The Kingdoms of this world are become the Kingdoms of our Lord and of his Christ, and he shall reign for ever and ever. And the four and twenty Elders which sate before God on their seats, fell upon their faces and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped God, saying, We give the thanks O Lord God Almighty, which art, and wast, and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:45884:46"/> art to come, because thou hast taken to thee thy great power and hast reigned.</hi> Rev. 19.1, 4, 6, 7, 8, 9, 16. <hi>And I heard as it were the voice of a great multitude, and as the voice of many waters, and as the voice of many Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings, saying, Alleluja, for the Lord God omnipotent reigneth. Let us be glad and rejoice, give honour to him, for the Marriage of the Lamb is come, and his wife hath made her self ready,</hi> Rev. 20.4, 5, 7, 9. <hi>And I saw Thrones, and they that sate upon them, and Judgement was given unto them. And I saw the souls of them that were beheaded for the Witness <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f Jesus, and for the Word of God, and which had not worshipped the Beast, neither his Image, neither had received his mark upon their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, or in their hands, and they lived and <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eigned with Christ a thousand years. But the rest <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the dead lived not again until the thousand <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ears were finished. This is the first Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n— And when the thousand years are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ired, Satan shall be loosed out of his prison— And they went upon the Breadth of the Earth, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd compassed the Camp of the Saints about, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd the Beloved City, and Fire came down from God out of Heaven and devoured them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Meditation.</hi> It is the Duty of all Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in-professors, <hi>especially</hi> sanctified Believers, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ho are wife Virgins,</hi> to go out and meet the <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ridegroom, when he comes by his spiritual
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:45884:47"/> power and glory in his Saints and Sanction, to set up his Kingdom and to reign on Farth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> The Lord Jesus Christ who is King of Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.3, King of <hi>Zion, Psal.</hi> 149.1, 2. and the King of Nations, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.7 shall be the only Potentate, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.14, 15. and King of all the Earth, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.9. And all the Kingdoms of the World shall be his, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. and his Saints, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14, 22, 27. And they shall reign with Christ on Earth a thousand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10 and <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The God of Heaven will set u<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this Kingdom of Christ and his Saints in th<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dayes of those Kings of the fourth Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy that oppose him and his Saints, <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2.24. And give it unto Christ as he is th<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Son of <hi>David,</hi> Luk. 1.32, 33. <hi>He shall b<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> great and shall be called the Son of the highe<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> and the Lord God shall give unto him t<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Throne of his Father</hi> David, <hi>and he shall reig<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> over the house of</hi> Jacob <hi>for ever, and of <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Kingdom there shall be no End. —A<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> unto the Saints of the most high.</hi> Dan. 7.2<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>And the Kingdom and Dominion, and <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> greatness of the Kingdom under the wh<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Heaven shall be given to the people of <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Saints of the most high, whose Kingd<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> is an Ev<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rlasting Kingdom, and all Do<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nions shall serve and obey him,</hi> who sh<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:45884:47"/> take it and possess it a thousand years.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> When Christ comes to set up his Kingdom and to reign on Earth Virtually and Spiritually in his Saints and Sanction, with power and great glory; It's the Duty of all Virgin-professors, especially sanctified Believers, <hi>who are wise Virgins</hi> to go out to meet the Bridegroom, <hi>ver.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>To meet the Bridegroom implies, 1. To be walking in the same way of Truth, wherein Christ comes, <hi>viz.</hi> To own that truth, and to witness unto that truth of the Kingdom, and power, and Glory of our Lord Jesus Christ, against the Kingdom, power, and Glory of Antichrist, which is the finishing Testimony of all the <hi>faithful</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses of Christ, Rev. 11.7. <hi>And when they shall have finished their Testimony, the Beast that ascendeth out of the Bottomless pit shall make war against them and overcome them and kill them.</hi> Which Testimony is that Gospel of the Kingdom of Christ that must be preached in all the World for a Witness unto all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To meet the Bridegroom implyes a progress and going on in that way of truth without weariness, fainting, sitting down and slumbering, Isa. 40.28, 29, 30, 31. <hi>Hast thou not known, hast thou not heard that the Everlasting God is LORD, the Creator of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:45884:48"/> the Ends of the Earth fainteth not, neither is weary. There is no searching of his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing— He giveth power to the faint, and to them that have no might be increaseth strength. Even the youth shall faint and be weary, and the young men shall utterly fail: but they that wait upon the Lord shall renew their strength, and they shall walk and not faint.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. To meet the Bridegroom implyes a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and continual watching and waiting for the virtual, spiritual, powerful and glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Christ the Bridegroom, Isa. 26.8, 9. <hi>Yea in the way of thy Judgements have we waited, O LORD have we waited for thee: The Desire of our soul is to thy name, and to the Remembrance of thee, in the night, yea with my Spirit within me will I seek thee Early; For when thy Judgements are in the Earth, the Inhabitants of the World will learn Righteousness.</hi> Habak. 2.3, 4. <hi>For the Vision is for an appointed time, but at the end it shall speak, and not lye: though it tarry, wait for it, because it will surely come, it will not tarry. Behold, his soul which is lifted up, is not upright in him; but the just shall live by his faith.</hi> Matth. 25.13. <hi>Watch therefore, for ye know neither the day, nor the hour wherein the Son of Man cometh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="verse">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:45884:48"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Vers. 7.</hi>
                     </bibl> Then all those Virgins arose and trimmed their Lamps, <hi>or cleansed their Lamps.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>The Virgins being awakened by the Cry at midnight, did all arise, <hi>that is to say,</hi> All those Virgin-professors began to shake off their carnal security, and rise from their beds of spiritual ease of sloth, and lazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and lukewarmness, Isa. 32.9. <hi>Rise up ye Women that are at ease,</hi> Cant. 3.2. And went out again to meet the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, as they were commanded, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. being glad to hear that Christ was now coming, in that midnight dispensation. They do as <hi>David</hi> did, Psal. 119.62. <hi>At midnight will I arise and give thanks unto thee.</hi> As <hi>Jonathan</hi> arose, and went to meet <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.16. So those Virgin-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors arose and went out again to meet the Bridegroom Christ Jesus the Son of <hi>David.</hi> Now the Virgins are awakened, and they call upon one another like the Watchmen of Mount <hi>Ephraim,</hi> saying, Jer. 31.6. <hi>Arise ye, and let us go up to</hi> Zion, <hi>unto Jehovah our God.</hi> The coming of Christ <hi>the Bridegroom</hi> will be a morning of such glorious light that shineth from
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:45884:49"/> one end of the Heavens unto the other, that will shine upon all the Virgin-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors, and cause the Wise Virgins to arise and shine as was Prophesied, Isa. 60.1, 2. <hi>Arise, shine, for thy light is come, and the glory of the LORD is risen upon thee. — For behold the darkness shall cover the Earth, and gross darkness the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but the LORD shall arise upon thee, and his glory shall be seen upon thee.</hi> And in order to their shining profession, the Virgins being risen are said to trim their Lamps.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And trimmed their Lamps.</hi> It seems whilest the Virgins slumbred and slept, their Lamps decayed; <hi>that is to say,</hi> The Oile in their Lamps wasted, and was spent, and the wiek and smoaking flax was burnt, and the light that had shined for some time, began to grow dim, and was going out, and some of their Lamps were gone out being foul and unsavoury, <hi>ver.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By trimming their Lamps</hi> is meant all the means and endeavours those Virgin-profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors used to cleanse and purge tneir Lamps, to supply them with Oyle, and wiek or flax, and so to repair their light, and prepare themselves to meet the Bridegroom, <hi>that is to say,</hi> Now that the Virgins are awakened and are risen up, they, <hi>especially</hi> the wise
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:45884:49"/> Virgins begin again to speak of the glory of Christs Kingdom, and to talk of his power, <hi>Psal.</hi> 145.10, 11, 12. and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themselves for the coming and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Christ. The wise Virgins having Oyle in their Vessels, get their Lamps sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed. And like the Bride, the Lambs Wife, Rev. 19.7, 8. they make themselves ready, ver. 10. And <hi>they that were ready went in with him,</hi> (with Christ the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom) <hi>into the Marriage.</hi> But the foolish Virgins having no Oyle in their Vessels, <hi>that is,</hi> They being without Christ, and having not the spiritual Unction of the Grace of God in their hearts, their Lamps went out, and they were shut out of the Marriage Chamber, <hi>ver.</hi> 10, 11, 12. Whilest they went to buy Oyle, even whilest they were seeking after Christ, Prov. 1.22, 23, 28. <hi>How long ye simple ones will ye love simplicity, and the scorners delight in their scorn, and fools hate knowledge? —Turn you at my reproof: Behold, I will pour out my Spirit upon you, I will make known my Words unto you. Then shall they call upon me, but I will not answer, they shall seek me early, but they shall not find me.</hi> And Luke 13.24, 25, 26, 27. <hi>Strive to enter in at the strait gate, for many I say unto you shall seek to enter in, and shall not be able.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:45884:50"/> When once the Master of the house is risen up and hath shut to the door, and ye begin to stand without and to knock at the door, saying, Lord, Lord open unto us, and he shall answer and say unto you, I know you not, whence you are; Then shall ye begin to say, We have eaten and drunk in thy presence, and thou hast taught in our streets — But he shall say, I tell you, I know you not whence you are, Depart from me all ye Workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Meditation.</hi> The publick Testimony of the nearness of Christs coming as the Bridegroom with <hi>spiritual</hi> power and <hi>great</hi> glory in his Saints and Sanction, will awaken and raise some Virgin-professors out of their Security, Backsliding and Apostasie.</p>
               <p>That there will be a Cry at midnight, <hi>viz.</hi> A loud voice from the Lord, a voice from the City, a voice from the Temple, <hi>to wit,</hi> a publick Ministerial testimony <hi>even</hi> in the midst of the Midnight Dispensation, and saying, Behold the Bridegroom cometh, hath been shewed in the Exposition of the sixth verse, and the words of this seventh verse testifie that loud voice or Cry did awake and cause the Virgins to Rise, <hi>Then all those virgins arose,</hi> to wit, out of the slumber and sleep of their sinful silence,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:45884:50"/> worldly ease, carnal security, careless for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, backsliding and Apostasie, and some of them with their Loins girt, and their Lamps burning, did arise and shine, and went out again to meet the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Meditation.</hi> That some of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin- professors shall be recovered out of their Security, Backsliding and Apostasie, and shall rise and shine at the coming of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ as the Bridegroom of his Church.</p>
               <p>God hath promised to heal the Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slidings of his People upon their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and returning to the Lord, Jer. 3.22. <hi>Return ye back-sliding Children, and I will heal your back-slidings: Behold we come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, for thou art the LORD our God,</hi> Hosea 14.1, 4. And he will cause the light of the knowledge of the glory of God to shine in their hearts, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. And make them shine in a holy Gospel-Conversation, <hi>Isa.</hi> 60.1, 2, 3. to the praise and glory of God, <hi>Arise, shine, for thy light is come, and the glory of the LORD is risen upon thee, — For behold the darkness shall cover the Earth, and gross darkness the people: but the LORD shall arise upon thee, and his Glory shall be seen upon thee. And
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:45884:51"/> Gentiles shall come to thy light, and Kings to the Brightness of thy Rising.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Meditation.</hi> It's the Duty of Virgin-professors and Church-members to prepare themselves for the coming of Christ as the Bridegroom, Matth. 24.44. <hi>Therefore be ye also ready, for in such an hour as you think not, the Son of Man cometh,</hi> Luk. 12.35, 36, 40. <hi>Let your Loins be girded about, and your lights burning. — And ye your selves like unto men that wait for the Lord, when he will return from the Wedding, that when he cometh and knocketh, they may open unto him immediately. Be ye therefore ready also, for the Son of Man cometh at an hour when ye think not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To be so prepared and ready, The wise Virgins must put on their beautiful Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Isa.</hi> 52.1. and rejoyce as <hi>Zion</hi> did, Isa. 61.10. <hi>I will greatly rejoice in the LORD my soul shall be joyful in my God for he hath cloathed me with the Garments of Salvation, he hath covered me with the Robe of Righteousness, as a Bridegroom decketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with ornaments, and as a Bride adorneth her self with her Jewels.</hi> And those that have spotted their Garments of profession by any sinful Conversation or complyance, ought to wash their Robes, and make
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:45884:51"/> them white in the blood of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.14. That so they all being cloathed with fine Linnen, white and clean (<hi>which is the Righteousness of the Saints,</hi> Rev. 19.8.) as a Bride adorned for her husband, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2. may walk with Christ in white. And (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus adorned and made ready to meet the Bridegroom) may be counted worthy to enter with him into the Marriage Chamber. Of this Preparation you will read more in <hi>ver.</hi> 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Vers. 8.</hi>
                     </bibl> And the foolish said unto the wise, Give us of your Oyle, for our Lamps are gone out.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>In these words consider 1. The Request that the foolish Virgins made unto the wise, <hi>Give us of your Oyle.</hi> 2. The Reason of their Request, <hi>For our Lamps are gone out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The foolish Virgin-professors were now <hi>at last</hi> made sensible that they wanted Oyle, and that it was their great folly that they did take no Oyle with them <hi>(as the wise Virgins did in their Vessels)</hi> when they took their Lamps, and went out to meet the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Meditation.</hi> It argues and demonstrates very great folly in those Virgin-professors,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:45884:52"/> and Church-members, who seem to be Religious, having a form of Godliness, and are looking for and bearing Testimony unto the spiritual Kingdom and glorious appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and coming of Christ the Churches Bridegroom, to be without Christ and to want the spirit of Christ, and the saving and sanctifying Grace of Jesus Christ in their hearts.</p>
               <p>Doubtless, Now at last the foolish Virgins were very sensible of their folly in resting sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied and contented with a profession of Christ, without a possession of Christ; with having their Lamps, and the form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, without the Oyle of Grace, and the power of Godliness; And with being in a Gospel Church State, and therein partaking of the holy Ordinances of God and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fellowship with the Wise Virgin-Saints, and yet not being partakers of the Divine Nature, nor having communion and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with God the Father, Son and holy Spirit in the wayes and Ordinances of God.</p>
               <p>Now those foolish Virgin-professors wish they had some of the wise Virgins Oyle; O, <hi>say they,</hi> that we had Christ, the Spirit of Christ, and the Grace of Christ in our hearts. Now they ask and beg, they seek unto and intreat the wise Virgin-Saints, <hi>saying, Give
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:45884:52"/> us of your Oyle,</hi> Communicate of your sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and sanctifying Graces to our souls.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Meditation.</hi> The time will come when foolish Professors and formal Church mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers will see and sadly experience their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without Christ, and their want of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Grace of God.</p>
               <p>Many Professors now can live without Christ, and without God, and without Grace in the World, yea in the Churches of Saints, and in the Ordinances of the Gospel, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times making a shining profession of Christ, and witnessing of, and bearing their testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the Kingdom and coming of the Lord Jesus Christ; and at other times slumbering and sleeping in a carnal security, luke-warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, formality and backsliding Apostasie: who when they are awakened by some mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night dispensation of God, will see and be convinced, and made sensible of their want and need of Christ, and the Spirit of Christ, and the Grace of Christ.</p>
               <p>The time will come when they shall see and know by a thorow conviction, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful experience that none but Christ, nothing but Grace will supply their wants, nor satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their souls. <hi>Give us of your Oyle:</hi> Oh! that we had possession of Christ as you have; Oh! that the saving sanctifying Grace of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:45884:53"/> God, and Spirit of God were in our hearts, as they are in yours; We now see our want of the power of Godliness, Truth of Grace, and Union and Communion with Christ, which you have and enjoy.</p>
               <p>And though Men and Women, yea some Professors and Church-members can live without Christ, buy and sell without Christ, build and plant without Christ, marry and give in marriage without Christ (for they will be very busie about such things, when the Son of Man cometh, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.26, 27, 28, 29, 30.) and some Professors can have and hold Communion with the Saints in the Churches and holy Ordinances of God, without Christ and Grace: Yet when Christ comes, yea when death comes, and they are awakened by that midnight dispensation, then they see themselves lost and undone to Eternity, then they know not what to do, nor how to dye without Christ and without Grace. Then they call, and cry, send for, and seek unto the Ministers and Saints of God, and say pray for us, speak to us, pity us, tell us what we shall do. O Men and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren <hi>what shall we do</hi> (as they did, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. And as the Jayler did, Acts 16.30. <hi>Sirs what shall I do to be saved?</hi> And as the foolish Virgins did here to the wise Virgins, <hi>Give us of your Oyle.</hi>)</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:45884:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For our Lamps are gone out;</hi> or are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, as in the Margent. This is the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of their Request; as if they had said, O ye wise Virgin-Saints, Sanctified Believers, who have Union with Christ, who have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the precious faith of Gods Elect, and have received the Grace of God in truth, and all the fruits of the Spirit; Give us of your Oyle, communicate some of your saving sanctifying Grace unto us. For our Lamps of professed Gospel-light, our shining Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-Light, all our spiritual Gifts and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Grace, all our former Gospel Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>even</hi> all our hopes and comforts are now decayed, withered, perished, and are ready to dye, and be utterly extinguished, and we our selves are in the dark, and must sit down and perish in eternal darkness, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less you can and will supply us with some of your spiritual Oyle; <hi>For our Lamps are gone out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Meditation.</hi> That all the Gospel-light, that shines in the spiritual gifts, and religious actions of foolish and formal professors, will at last be extinguished, and go out, and they will fall away.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There are some formal Professors that have received spiritual Gifts from God, 1 Cor. 12.4. to the 11 verse, <hi>Now there are diversities of gifts, but the same Spirit, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:45884:54"/> there are differences of Administrations, but the same Lord— And there are diversities of Operations, but it is the same God that worketh all in all— But the manifestation of the Spirit, is given to every Man to profit withal. For to one is given by the Spirit the Word of Wisdom, to another the word of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, by the same spirit — To another faith by the same spirit, to another the gift of healing by the same spirit, to another the working of Miracles, to another Prophesie, to another discerning of Spirits, to another divers kinds of Tongues, to another the Interpretation of tongues.</hi> One member of the Church may have a word of knowledge, another may have a word of Wisdom, another may have a gift of Prophesie, another may have faith <hi>(not sanctifying faith)</hi> and all these and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Gifts given them by the holy Spirit of God, and yet not have Christ, nor the Graces of faith and Love in Christ Jesus, 1 Cor. 13.1, 2, 3. <hi>Though I speak with the tongues of Men and of Angels, and have not Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, I am become as sounding brass or a tink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Cymbal. And though I have the gifts of prophesie, and understand all Mysteries, and all knowledge, and though I have all faith, so that I could remove Mountains, and have not Charity, I am nothing. And though I bestow all my goods to feed the poor, and though I
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:45884:54"/> give my Body to be burned, and have not Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, it profiteth me nothing.</hi> Gal. 5.6. <hi>For in Jesus Christ, neither Circumcision availeth any thing, nor uncircumcision, but faith which worketh by Love.</hi> The Apostle in these words, <hi>Neither Circumcision availeth any thing,</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and testifieth that no Priviledges, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Gifts or Administrations that the Jews had under the Law; <hi>Nor Ʋncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> that is to say, no Priviledges, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Gifts or Administrations, which the Gentiles have under the Gospel, will profit or avail them any thing in order unto the obtaining of Eternal Life, and Everlasting Salvation, without faith in Christ Jesus, that works by Love, or as <hi>Paul</hi> saith, Gal. 6.15. <hi>For in Christ Jesus, neither Circumcision avail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any thing, nor uncircumcision, but a new Creature;</hi> that is, unless the professing Jew or Gentile be <hi>a new Creature,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17. that is, Gods Workmanship created in Christ Jesus unto good Works, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.10. that we should walk in them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And some foolish and formal Virgin-professors may shine <hi>for a season</hi> in the Acts and Exercise of those spiritual gifts that they have received from God for the Churches Edification, 1 Cor. 14.1, &amp; 3. <hi>Follow after Charity, and desire spiritual gifts, but rather that ye may Prophesie. — But he that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:45884:55"/> Prophesieth speaketh unto men to Edification, and Exhortation and Comfort.</hi> And they may also shine in some kind and degree of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel-like conversation, and Saint-like life, in respect of some external actions and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward performance of holy duties. And they may likewise shine like Lamps and Temple-lights in bearing their Witness and Testimony for Christ, his Head-ship, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry, Churches, Worship, Kingdom and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. And lastly, they may shine like Lamps and burning Lights in enduring the Afflictions of the Gospel, in suffering the spoyling of their goods, imprisonment, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, yea and death it self, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And yet after all this their Lamps will go out, and those foolish and formal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors will fall away, Luk. 8.13. <hi>They on the Rock are they which when they hear, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Word with Joy, and these have no Root, which for a time believe, and in time of temptation fall away.</hi> Those hard hearted hearers <hi>believed for a time,</hi> They made a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of the faith of the Gospel, and they made a confession too, and that before many Witnesses; <hi>But in time of temptation fell away.</hi> When that hour of temptation comes upon them which Christ hath foretold shall come upon all the world, to try them that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:45884:55"/> dwell upon the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.10. then they will fall away; and the Reason is, because <hi>they have no Root,</hi> that is, they have not Christ, they are not rooted in him, Col. 2.6, 7. <hi>As ye have therefore received Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus the Lord, so walk ye in him: Rooted and built up in him, stablished in the faith: as ye have been taught, abounding therein with thanksgiving.</hi> Faith in Christ never falls away, 1 Pet. 1.3, 4, 5. <hi>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, which according to his abundant Mercy hath begotten us again unto a lively hope by the Resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead, to an Inheritance incorruptible and undefiled, and that fadeth not away, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served in Heaven for you, who are kept by the mighty power of God, through faith unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, ready to be revealed in the last time.</hi> It's a faith without Christ that foolish Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors depart from, 1 Tim. 4.1. <hi>Now the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit speaketh expresly, that in the later times some shall depart from the faith, giving heed to seducing Spirits and Doctrines of Devils.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="verse">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:45884:56"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Vers. 9:</hi>
                     </bibl> But the Wise answered, saying, Not so, lest there be not enough for us and you, but go ye rather to them that sell, and buy for your selves.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>This Verse contains the Answer that the Wise Virgins gave to the request of the Foolish Virgins. Wherein,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They gave them a denyal, and the reason thereof; <hi>But the Wise answered, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Not so;</hi> We may not, we cannot grant what you desire of us, <hi>lest there be not enough for us and you.</hi> As if the Wise Virgins had said, It's true indeed, we have Oyle in our Vessels, and supply for our Lamps; But we can spare none, our Vessels have no more Oyle in them than we do and shall need for our selves, <hi>Not so.</hi> The Lord Jesus Christ hath given us his saving and sanctifying Grace, but we may not, we cannot give it to you, no not the least measure of it; not a dram nor a drop can we give, nor can we spare any of it, we stand in need to get more grace for our selves, lest we should not have enough in those hours and times of Tryals, that we may meet with yet, ere we meet with the Bridegroom; and lest we have not enough for those services of Christ, and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:45884:56"/> sufferings for Christ that our Lord may call us to either before his coming, or when he comes, or after he is come as the Bridegroom.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They gave the foolish Virgins Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons what to do in their condition, <hi>But go ye rather to them that sell and buy for your selves,</hi> Wherein we are to consider, 1. Who they are that sell this spiritual Oyle? 2. What it is to buy it?</p>
               <p>The spiritual Oyle is the Unction of the holy one, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.20, 27. That wherewith Christ was anointed above his fellows, <hi>Psal.</hi> 45.7. <hi>viz.</hi> the saving, sanctifying Grace of God, the gifts and fruits of the holy Spirit, of which read the Exposition of <hi>vers.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>They that sell this Mystical and Spiritual Oyle, are Christ, and his Ministers, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. The Lord Jesus Christ is the owner of this Oyle, and he himself doth sometimes sell it, or offer it to sale, as he did to the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> Rev. 3.18. <hi>I counsel thee to buy of me Gold tried in the fire, that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est be <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ch, and white Rayment, that thou mayest be cloathed, and that the shame of thy naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness do not appear, and anoint thine eyes with eye salve, that thou mayest see.</hi> But ordinarily and commonly Christ authorizeth and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth his faithful Servants (the Ministers of the Gospel) whom he appointeth, commissioneth and sends to offer this
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:45884:57"/> spiritual Oyle to sale, and to sell it unto whomsoever will buy it, Isa. 51.1. <hi>Hearken to me, ye that follow after righteousness, ye that seek the Lord: look unto the rock whence ye are hewen, and to the hole of the pit whence ye are digged.</hi> Joh. 7.37. <hi>In the last day, that great day of the feast, Jesus stood, and cryed, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, If any man thirst, let him come unto me and drink.</hi> Rev. 22.17. <hi>And the Spirit and the Bride say Come. And let him that heareth, say Come. And let him that is athirst, come. And whomsoever will, let him take the water of life freely.</hi> For as it was a great sin in <hi>Simon Magus</hi> to offer money, and to think that the gifts of the Holy Ghost might be bought for material money, so it is a very great sin in any Minister to sell this Mystical Oyle for material Silver or Gold, or any price or earthly commodity. And it is a very great mistake in foolish Professors, to think they may buy, <hi>that is,</hi> bargain with God for Christ and Grace upon the terms of the old Covenant of works, and their own Righteousness, which is as menstruous raggs, <hi>Isa.</hi> 64.6.</p>
               <p>To buy this spiritual Oyle, Implyes three things, 1. A sense of want and need of it, which the foolish Virgins now had. 2. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending upon the Ministry of the Word and Administrations of the Gospel to obtain it,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:45884:57"/> or to get some of this Oyle, having their heart and hand open and willing to receive it, Acts 16.14. <hi>And a certain Woman named</hi> Lydia <hi>a seller of Purple of the City of</hi> Thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atira, <hi>which worshipped God heard us, whose heart the Lord opened that she attended unto the things which were spoken of</hi> Paul. 3. A willingness to have it upon Christs own terms of free Grace, without money and without price, Isa. 55.1, 2, 3. &amp; Rev. 21.6.22.7. <hi>Ho<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> every one that thirsteth, come ye to the waters. And he that hath no money, come ye buy and eat, yea come, buy wine and milk without money, and with<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut price. Wherefore do ye spend money f<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r that which is not bread, and your labour for that which satisfieth not? hearken dilig<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntly unto me, and eat that which is good, and let your soul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light it self in fatness. — Encline your Eare and hear, and come unto me, and your soul shall live, and I will make an everlasting Covenant with you even the sure Mercies of</hi> David. — <hi>And he said unto me, it is done, I am</hi> Alpha <hi>and</hi> Omega, <hi>the beginning and the end: I will give unto him that is athirst of the fountain of the water of life freely — And the Spirit and the Bride say come, and let him that heareth say come, and let him that is athirst come, and whosoever will, let him take the water of life freely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:45884:58"/>1. <hi>Meditation.</hi> That Virgin-Saints who have the greatest and fullest measure of Grace and Holiness, cannot give or impart any of it unto others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Foolish said unto the Wise, give us of your Oyle;</hi> that is, Impart some of your Grace unto us: but the Wise answered and said, <hi>Not so,</hi> we cannot give you Grace, nor can we impart any of our Grace to you. Oh! saith a dying Father, Mother, or some other Relation, I am without Christ, I have no Grace, I am ready to dye and be damned, and I shall perish to all Eternity. O Dear Wife, Child, Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, or other Godly Relation, that my soul were in your souls condition. Oh! speak comfort and peace to me: Oh! that I had Christ, Grace, Pardon or any hopes of Eternal Life. But then those Godly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations must say, <hi>It is not in me,</hi> I cannot impart any Grace to you; Christ must give you of his Spirit, and God must give you of his Grace, I cannot.</p>
               <p>Godly Parents and Relations may and ought to pray that God will give pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace, sanctifying Grace, saving Grace to their Children, or to any other Relations but they cannot give any, nor can they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part any Grace to them.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:45884:58"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> could not give Grace to <hi>Ish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael,</hi> nor could <hi>Isaac</hi> impart Grace to <hi>Esau,</hi> nor <hi>Jacob</hi> to <hi>Reuben;</hi> no, nor <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> to <hi>Absolom,</hi> nor <hi>Job</hi> to his Wife: Neither could <hi>Paul</hi> impart Grace to his Countrey-men, for whom his hearts desire and Prayer was, that they might be saved; and although he was willing to be accursed for them, as the holy Scriptures of Truth testifie.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Meditation.</hi> Every Saint and sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Believer will <hi>(ere he get to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven)</hi> stand in need of all the Grace he hath.</p>
               <p>Sanctified Believers, called Saints, may meet with such fiery tryals, such hellish Temptations, such powerful stirrings of corruptions, and so great variety of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, Tribulations, Persecutions and Sufferings; yea such hours and powers of darkness, and so deep Desertions that vvill call for and require the Virgins lively Acts and Exercise of all the Grace of God they have; yea, and they may be necessitated to go to Christ for more Grace as the Apostle did, 2 Cor. 12.7, 8, 9. <hi>And lest I should be exalted above measure through the abundance of the Revelations, there was given to me a thorn in the flesh, the Messenger of Satan to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:45884:59"/> buffet me, lest I should be exalted above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. For this thing I besought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from me: And he said unto me, My Grace is sufficient for thee for my strength is made perfect in weakness. Most gladly therefore will I rather glory in my Infirmities, that the power of Christ may rest upon me.</hi> Believers will have need of all the Grace they have, when they come to dye, and be dissolved.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Meditation.</hi> It's the duty of every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, that sees their need and want of Christ, his holy Spirit, and sanctifying Grace to attend upon the Ministry of the Gospel and Administrations of the holy Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God, and to accept and receive Christ and Grace offered freely without money or price.</p>
               <p>Many sinners are so blinded 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4. that they see no form nor comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in Christ; and when they do see some beauty and excellency in him, yet they are apt to refuse and reject him, until they be throughly convinced of their want and need of him, his Spirit and Grace, and <hi>that there is not salvation in any other,</hi> Acts 4.12. And then they begin to desire and say, Oh! that I had Christ, Oh! that I had Grace, Oh! that I could believe. Now it is their
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:45884:59"/> Duty to attend diligently and conscionably upon the Ministry of the Gospel and means of Grace; for faith comes by Hearing the Word Preached, Rom. 10.17. Acts 14.1. Isa. 55.3. <hi>Incline your Eare, come unto me, hear and your souls shall live. And I will make an everlasting Covenant with you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And as it is their Duty to hear, so it is their Duty to believe, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.23. and by faith to accept and receive Jesus Christ of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to them upon Gospel terms of free Grace, without money and without price, Joh. 1.11, 12. <hi>He came unto his own, and his own received him not, but as many as received him, to them gave he power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Sons of God, even to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on his Name</hi> Rev. 22.17. <hi>And the Spirit and the Bride say come, and let him that heareth say come, and whosoever will, let him take the water of life freely:</hi> and <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.1, 2, 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="verse">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:45884:60"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Vers. 10.</hi>
                     </bibl> And while they went to buy, the Bridegroom came, and they that were ready went in with him to the Marriage, and the door was shut.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>The foolish Virgins followed the Counsel of the wise and went to buy Oyle for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; and so do many formal and foolish Professors <hi>(when they are convinced of their sins, and of their necessity of a Saviour)</hi> then they seek after Christ and cry for grace, and call upon God for pardoning mercy and salvation, but it's too late it may be, Prov. 1.24, 28. <hi>Because I have called and ye refused, I have stretched out my hand and no man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded—Then shall they call upon me, but I will not answer, they shall seek me early but they shall not find me. And while they went to buy, the Bridegroom came.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And they that were ready went in with him to the Marriage, and the door was shut.</hi> They that were duly prepared for the Bridegrooms coming had an entrance admitted to them into his Kingdom, and all others were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They that were ready</hi> had put off the filthy raggs of their own Righteousness, and had
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:45884:60"/> put on the Robes of Christs Righteousness, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.14. God had taken away their filthy garments and had cloathed them with change of raiment, <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.3, 4. Thus <hi>Zion</hi> the holy City the New <hi>Jerusalem</hi> is called upon and commanded by the LORD her Maker, her Husband and her Redeemer to loose her self from the Bands of her Neck, her <hi>Captivity,</hi> to arise and put on her beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful garments, <hi>Isa.</hi> 52.1, 2, 3. And so she shall do with great Joy and rejoycing. And therefore she is <hi>prophetically</hi> said to do so, Isa. 61.10. <hi>I will greatly rejoice in the LORD, my soul shall be joyful in my God, for he hath cloathed me with the Garments of salvation, he hath covered me with the Robes of Righteousness; as a Bridegroom adorneth himself with Ornaments, and as a Bride deck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her self with her Jewels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to be prepared for the Bridegrooms coming is to be arrayed in fine Linnen, white and clean, which is the Righteousness of the Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7, 8. And so the holy City, the New <hi>Jerusalem</hi> was prepared as a Bride adorned for her Husband in <hi>John</hi>'s Vision, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2. Of this glorious Marriage and <hi>mysterie of Christ and his Church, David</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesied, <hi>Psal.</hi> 45. Wherein we have this great and glorious solemnity of the Bridegrooms coming, and of the Marriage of the Lamb
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:45884:61"/> Mystically and Metaphorically sung and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned down by that sweet finger of <hi>Israel</hi> in that <hi>(Epithalamium)</hi> Love song, or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage-song, Psal. 45.1, 2, 6, 8, 9, 13, 14. <hi>My heart is inditing a good matter, I speak of the things which I have made touching the King. My tongue is the pen of a ready writer. —Thou art fairer than the Children of Men; Grace is poured into thy Lips therefore God hath blessed thee for ever. Thy Throne O God is for ever and ever, and the Scepter of thy Kingdom is a right Scepter. All thy Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments smell of Myrrhe, and Aloes, and Cassia, out of the Ivory places whereby they have made thee glad. Kings Daughters were among thy honourable Women. Ʋpon thy right hand did stand the Queen in Gold of</hi> Ophir. <hi>The Kings Daughter is all glorious within, her Cloathing is of wrought Gold. —She shall be brought unto the King in Raiment of Needle-work; the Virgins her Companions that follow her, shall be brought unto thee; with gladness and rejoycing they shall enter into the Kings Palace.</hi> And so the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> (describing the Churches condition, from her Cradle to her Crown, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.13-14.) speaks of her inward and spiritual beauty and glory under divers Metaphors and figurative Expressions, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. to the end of the 14. <hi>Now when I passed by thee, and looked upon thee; Behold thy
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:45884:61"/> time was the time of Love. And I spread my skirt over thee; and covered thy Nakedness; yea, I sware unto thee, and entred into a Covenant with thee saith the Lord God, and th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camest mine. Then washed I thee with water, yea I throughly washed away thy blood from thee, and I anointed thee with Oyle, I cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee also with broidered work, and shod thee with Badgers skin, and I girded thee about with fine Linnen, and I covered thee with silk, and decked thee also with Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and I put Bracelets upon thine hands, and a Chain on thy neck, and I put a Jewel on thy forehead, and Ear-rings in thine Ears, and a beautiful Crown upon thine Head Thus wast thou decked with God and Silver and thy Raiment was of fine Linnen, and silk, and broidered work; thou didst eat fine flower and honey and Oyle, and thou wast exceeding beautiful. And thou didst prosper into a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. — And thy renown went forth among the Heathen, for thy Beauty was perfect through my Comeliness which I had put upon thee, saith the Lord GOD.</hi> This Prophesie in the Mysterie of it will be fulfilled when the Bridegroom cometh, for then Christ will put on a beautiful Crown upon her head, and she will be exceeding beautiful, and she shall then prosper into a Kingdom, Isa. 28.5. <hi>In that day shall the LORD be for a Crown
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:45884:62"/> of Glory, and for a Diadem of Beauty, unto the residue of his people.</hi> Isa. 62.3. <hi>Thou shalt also be a Crown of glory in the hand of the LORD, and a Royal Diadem in the hand of thy God.</hi> When will this day of <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> glory be? <hi>then it will be,</hi> when the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom cometh, and marries his Bride, Isa. 62 5. <hi>For as a young man marrieth a Virgin, so shall sons marry thee, and as the Bridegroom rejoyceth over the Bride, so shall thy God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over thee.</hi> And thus the wise Virgin-saints were prepared and ready, <hi>and went in with him to the marriage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the door was shut.</hi> There is the Door of Grace, and that is all opportunities and seasons that the Ministers of Christ have and improve to preach, and the people have and improve to hear the Gospel of the Grace of God; also to administer and partake of the holy Ordinances of God in any place, and at any time, called an open Door, Rev. 3.8. <hi>A great Door and Effectual is opened,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 16.9. and 2 Cor. 2.12. <hi>And a Door was opened to me of or by the Lord.</hi> That was a door of Grace. And when God removes the Candlestick, takes away the Gospel, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the Adversaries to silence and perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his faithful Ministers and Churches of Saints, when their Ministers by Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Banishment are removed into Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:45884:62"/> and their Eyes cannot see their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, when the people run to and fro, to seek the Word of the Lord, and cannot find it, then the Door of Grace is shut.</p>
               <p>There is also the Door of the Kingdom of Christ, Luk. 13.25, 26, 27, 28, 29. <hi>When once the Master of the house is risen up and hath shut to the door, and ye begin to stand without and to knock at the door, saying, LORD, LORD, open unto us, and he shall answer and say unto you, I know you not, whence you are; Then shall ye begin to say, we have eaten and drunk in thy presence, and thou hast taught in our streets, but he shall say, I tell you I know you not, whence you are; depart from me all ye workers of iniquity. There shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth, when ye shall see</hi> Abraham, <hi>and</hi> Isaac, <hi>and</hi> Jacob, <hi>and all the Prophets in the Kingdom of God, and you your selves thrust out. And they shall come from the East, and from the West, and from the North, and from the South, and shall sit down in the Kingdom of God.</hi> This is the <hi>door</hi> that was shut here in my text, <hi>to wit,</hi> the door of Christs marriage Chamber, <hi>that is to say,</hi> an entrance and admittance into the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Kingdom of our Lord Jesus Christ, 2 Pet. 1.10, 11. <hi>Wherefore the rather Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren give diligence to make your Calling and Election sure, for if ye do these things, ye shall
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:45884:63"/> never fail, for so an entrance shall be ministred unto you abundantly, into the everlasting Kingdom of the Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Meditation.</hi> That all persons, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Virgin-professors ought to prepare, and to be ready, when <hi>Christ the Churches Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom cometh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this end, 1. Sinners, you must get Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, if you will not receive and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain Christ into your hearts, by faith, a true penitent and lively faith, he will not receive and admit you into the Marriage Chamber of his Kingdom, when he comes <hi>as the Bridegroom.</hi> If sinners will not let Christ live in them, and reign in them, in the Kingdom of his grace now, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.20, 21. they shall not live and reign with him in his Kingdom, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. Christ will shut the door of his Kingdom against them that shut the door of their hearts against him.</p>
               <p>Therefore Sinners, whilest Jesus Christ stands at the door, open the door of your hearts to Christ, and let him come and set up the Kingdom of his Grace in your hearts according to his gracious promise, Rev. 3.20, 21, 22. <hi>Behold, I stand at the door and knock, if any man hear my voice, and open the door, I will come into him and sup with
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:45884:63"/> him, and he with me. —To him that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh, will I grant to sit with me in my Throne, even as I also overcame, and am set down with my Father in his Throne. He that hath an Ear, let him hear what the spirit saith unto the Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Saints, you ought to prepare and be ready to meet Christ <hi>the Churches Bridegroom,</hi> when he cometh, and therefore consider what you have to do ere you and Jesus Christ meet in his Marriage Kingdom. O gracious and precious Saints, have you not something to do ere you dye? Can you heartily desire and earnestly pray to be dissolved and be with Christ before you have overcome the world, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.4, 5. go the victory over sin, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56.57. and resisted, vanquished, and made a conquest over the Devil, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.13, 14. and in all these to be more than Conquerours through Christ Jesus our Lord? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37. Can you expect to inherit all things, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. until you have overcome all things? our Lord Jesus Christ overcame before he sate down with the Father in his Throne. And will Jesus Christ grant you to sit down with him in his Throne, untill you have also overcome? <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21, 22.</p>
               <p>Again consider Saints, are you <hi>prepared</hi> as a Bride adorned for her Husband? <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2, 3. Are you cloathed in fine Linnen, white
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:45884:64"/> and clean, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.8. and so made <hi>Ready</hi> for the Marriage of the Lamb? <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7. Or do not some of you stand in need to w<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sh your <hi>Robes</hi> and make them white in the blood of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.14, 15. before you can put on your <hi>beautiful</hi> garments, <hi>Isa.</hi> 52.1, 2. and adorn your selves with Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as a Bride, <hi>Isa.</hi> 61.10. or as the Bride-maidens, the Virgins her Companions? <hi>Psal.</hi> 45.9, 13, 14.</p>
               <p>The LORD first washed his people with water, yea, he throughly washed away their blood from them, and anointed them with Oyle, and then he cloathed them with broidered work, girded them with Linnen and covered them with silk. He decked them also with Ornaments, Bracelets, Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, chains of Gold and Pearl about their neck, and at last he put a beautiful Crown upon the Churches head, and they prospered into a Kingdom, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.9-14. So the Apostle testifieth, That Jesus Christ gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self for his Church <hi>that he might sanctifie it, and cleanse it with the washing of water by the ward, that he might present it to himself a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Church, not having spot or wrinkle, or any such thing, but that it should be holy and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blemish.</hi> O beloved and blessed Virgin Saints, how much cleansing, purging, sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying work is there yet to be done in your
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:45884:64"/> souls by the spirit, and word of God in the lively and powerful applications of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood of Jesus Christ, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>and Heb.</hi> 13.12. <hi>and</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.9.</p>
               <p>Once more consider saints, O ye wise Virgins, are your Vessels full of Oyle? Are your hearts full of Grace, have you perfected holiness in the fear of God? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. And are you come in the Unity of faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect man? <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.13. If not, you are not yet so prepared, nor are you yet so ready as you should desire and endeavour to be, and may be through the Communication of the exceeding riches of the grace of God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.7. and the unsearchable riches of Jesus Christ, you may attain to be ere the Bridegroom come.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Meditation.</hi> Whilest some foolish and negligent Virgin-professors are seeking too late to get, and endeavouring too late to buy the spiritual Oyle of Grace to supply their Lamps, Christ will come, and shut the Door of his Grace and Kingdom against them, <hi>And the Door was shut.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some Professors being careless and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent when they enjoy powerful means of Grace, <hi>(as the foolish Virgins were when they first went out to meet the Bridegroom,)</hi> content
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:45884:65"/> themselves and are satisfied with some spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual gifts without grace, and the form of Godliness without the power of it <hi>(as the foolish Virgins did that took their Lamps, but took no Oyle with them.)</hi> And so go on in the broad way of an outward customary and formal performance of holy duties and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of Gospel Ordinances all the Day of Grace, until the night of security, ease and darkness overtake them, and they begin to slumber and fall fast asleep in their formality, or in their Apostasie, until in some midnight dispensation, a Cry with a loud voice from the Lord, from the City or from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, awaken them and affright them; And then they perceive that their Lamps are gone out, and that they themselves are in a state of darkness, wanting Christ and Grace in their souls <hi>(as the foolish Virgins who want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Oyle in their Vessels and went to buy it.)</hi> So some formal Professors, <hi>when it is too late,</hi> seek for Grace and enquire after Christ; say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as <hi>Balaam</hi> did, <hi>Let me dye the death of the righteous, and let my last end be like his,</hi> Numb. 23.10. But their day of Grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing past, Christ shuts the door of Grace, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>He that is unjust let him be unjust still, and he that is filthy, let him be filthy still,</hi> Rev. 22.11. And Christ will when he comes <hi>as
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:45884:65"/> the Bridegroom</hi> shut the door of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom against those foolish Virgin-professors, who refused the Offers, Call and Invitations of the Gospel in the day of Grace, read <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.20. to the end of the Chapter. Vers. 24, 25, 28. <hi>Because I have called and ye refused, I have stretched out my hand and no man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded. —But ye have set at nought all my Counsel, and would none of my reproof. Then shall they call upon me, but I will not answer; they shall seek me early, but they shall not find me.</hi> And as doth plainly appear in the 11 and 12 Verses of this Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11, 12" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Vers. 11, 12.</hi>
                     </bibl> Afterward came also the other Virgins, saying, LORD, LORD, open unto us: But he answered and said, Verily I say unto you, I know you not.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Afterwards, <hi>or last of all,</hi> that, is after the wise Virgin-saints were entred into the Marriage Chamber with Christ <hi>the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom of his Church,</hi> and after the door of the Kingdom of Christ was shut, then came the foolish Virgin-professors, a multitude <hi>or very many</hi> formalists and Hypocrites, <hi>saying, Lord, Lord, open to us.</hi> They called and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:45884:66"/> cryed earnestly, prayed and beseeched the Lord Jesus Christ again and again to open the door of his Kingdom unto them, and let them have an entrance admitted into his Everlasting Kingdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But he answering, said, Verily I say unto you, I know you not.</hi> As they were earnest in their Request, so was Christ very positive in his Answer, <hi>Verily,</hi> assuredly, indeed and and truth, <hi>I know you not,</hi> I love you not, I do not approve of you, I own you not to be of the number of those that my Father gave me, and whom I redeemed with my blood, and whom I called and sanctified by my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Grace, and who sought to worship God by the Spirit and in truth, I know you not to be the adopted Children of my Father, justified and sanctified by faith that is in me. You are Formalists and Hypocrites, impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Backsliders and Apostates, who have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed my Headship, my Kingly Office, and would not that I should reign over you. In a word, you are workers of Iniquity, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me,</hi> I profess I do not know you, so as to approve of you, to own you, to open the door of my Kingdom to you, Luke 13.24, 25, 26, 27. <hi>Strive to enter in at the strait Gate, for many I say unto you, will seek to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in and shall not be able. —When once the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:45884:66"/> Master of the house is risen up and hath shut to the door, and ye begin to stand without, and to knock at the door, saying, Lord, Lord, open unto us, and he shall answer and say unto you, I know you not whence you are. Then shall ye begin to say, We have eaten and drunken in thy presence, and thou hast taught in our streets, —But He shall say, I tell you know you not whence you are, Depart from me ye workers of Iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meditation.</hi> It will be a sad astonishing and miserably woful condition, that all foolish Virgin-Professors will be in, when the Lord Jesus Christ shall exclude them and shut them out of his Kingdom, and disown them for ever.</p>
               <p>Virgin-Professors having a strong confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>Hosea</hi> 1.8. and great hope and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19. of the pardon of all their Sins, and of Eternal life and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then at last find by woful experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that the Lord hath rejected their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.37. and their expectations be in vain and perish, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.28. and their hope like the Spiders Web, Job 8.13, 14. <hi>For what is the hope of the Hypocrite, when God shall take away his soul,</hi> Job 27.8. and that God will not forgive their Iniquities, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.10. <hi>and</hi> 16.18. but will give them
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:45884:67"/> the wages of their sins, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them according to their evil deeds, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6, 9, 11. yea and they having had a strong perswasion or presumption, rather that when Christ comes, they shall have an entrance admitted to them into his everlasting Kingdom; and at last Christ comes, and shuts the door of the Kingdom, and then they come and knock, and say Lord, Lord, open to us, and be denyed and repulsed, and Christ tell them he knows them not, and say depart from me ye Hypocrites, ye formal Professors, ye foolish Virgins, and all ye workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, what an amazement and astonishment will it be to them? And then <hi>they will begin to say, LORD we have eat and drunk in thy presence, and thou hast taught in our streets,</hi> Luk. 13.26, 27. <hi>That is,</hi> we have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Ministry of the Gospel, and all the Administrations thereof. We have been often at the Lords Table, and have been par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of all the holy Ordinances of God, Matth. 7.21, 22, 23. <hi>Not every one that saith, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, but he that doth the will of my Father which is in Heaven. — Many will say unto me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesied in thy name, and in thy name have done many wondrous works, and then will I profes
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:45884:67"/> unto them, I never knew you, depart from me ye that work Iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Vers. 13.</hi>
                     </bibl> Watch therefore, for ye know neither the day nor the hour wherein the Son of man cometh.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>This Verse contains the use that Christ would have his Disciples make of this Parable and of his Doctrine therein contained, and that is to watch, <hi>Watch ye therefore,</hi> which exhortation he urgeth from their ignorance of the time when Christ, <hi>the Churches Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom,</hi> will come, <hi>For ye know neither the day, nor the hour wherein the Son of man cometh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From whence two propositions, do arise, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That the time of Christ his coming <hi>as the Bridegroom</hi> is not known to any Saint or Angel, but to the Father only.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it's the Duty of all Christs Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to be watching and waiting daily for the glorious appearance of Christ, who will come as the Bridegroom of his Church.</p>
               <p>Touching the first Proposition, read Mat. 24.36. Mark 13.32. <hi>But of that day, and that hour knoweth no man, no not the Angels which are in Heaven, neither the Son but the Father</hi>— Though God the Father hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:45884:68"/> the knowledge of the day and hour of Christ, the <hi>Bridegrooms</hi> coming in his own <hi>secret decree,</hi> yet hath he given forth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed some signs of his coming which are <hi>recorded</hi> in the holy Scriptures of truth, which his Disciples being desirous to know, asked him saying, <hi>And what shall be the sign of thy coming?</hi> Matth. 24.3. Unto which question Christ answered many things, but more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly he told them, 1. That his Saints and Servants should suffer great persecutions, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.9. <hi>&amp; Luk.</hi> 21.12, 16, 17. 2. That Iniquity shall abound, and the Love of many will wax cold, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.12. 3. That the Gospel of the Kingdom shall be Preached in all the World, for a Witness unto all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.14. 4. That then shall be great Tribulation, such as never was, no nor ever shall be, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.21. And immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after the tribulation of those dayes the powers of Heaven shall be shaken, and then the shall appear the sign of Son of man in Heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.29, 30.</p>
               <p>Touching the second Proposition, read, Matth. 24.42. &amp; 25.13. Luk. 21.36. <hi>Watch ye therefore, and pray alwayes that ye may be accounted worthy to escape all those things that shall come to pass and to stand before the Son of man.</hi> They that would be accounted
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:45884:68"/> worthy to stand before Christ the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, when he comes, must watch and pray continually.</p>
               <p>Watching impli<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, 1. That Professors, Christs Disciples ought to be awake, Rom. 13.11. <hi>And that knowing the time that now it is high time to awake out of sleep, for now is our salvation nearer than when we believed.</hi> 1 Thes. 5.2, 6. <hi>For your selves know perfectly, That the day of the Lord so cometh as a thief in the night.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That Professors are to be in a continual expectation of Christ his glorious appearance <hi>as they that watch for the morning,</hi> Psal. 130.5, 6. <hi>I wait for the Lord: my soul doth wait, and in his word do I hope. My soul waiteth for the Lord, more than they that watch for the morning, I say, more than they that watch for the morning.</hi> And Luk. 12.35, 36, 37, 38. <hi>Let your Loins be girded about, and your Lamps burning. — And ye your selves like unto men that wait for their Lord when he will return from the Wedding, that when he cometh and knocketh, they may open unto him immediately. Blessed are those Servants, whom the Lord when he cometh shall find watching. Verily, I say unto you that he shall gird himself, and make them to sit down to meat, and will come forth and serve them. And if he shall come in the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:45884:69"/> second watch, or come in the third watch, and find them so, blessed are those servants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That Professors be looking out, desirous of and longing for the coming and Kingdom of Christ, 2 Pet. 3.11, 12. <hi>Looking for and hasting unto the coming of the day of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Watching is a necessary Duty incumbent upon Christians at all times, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.36. in all things, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. It's our duty in every duty; We ought to watch and pray, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.41. to watch unto prayer, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7. and to watch after prayer, and wait for the return and answer of our prayers. Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ought to watch their hearts, thoughts and affections; they ought to set a watch before the door of their Lips, that their Tongues do not offend, and they ought to watch their lives and conversations in their callings and imployments in the World. But especially Christians ought to watch for the glorious appearance of the Bridegroom, our Lord Jesus Christ, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.42. And they ought to be in a watching posture, and upon watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing work or duty, <hi>especially,</hi> when they hear of his near approach. Yea, and it is the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Believers, to be upon their watch all the <hi>Mystical</hi> night, until the Bridegroom come.</p>
               <p>The word, <hi>Watch,</hi> is borrowed from Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, or Souldiers, or Sea-men, or Porters,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:45884:69"/> or Citizens, who use, to watch in the night season. The Jews divided the night into 3 Watches, whereof the first began at Twilight, and continued till Midnight, called the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi> of the watches, <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.19. the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond watch began at midnight, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed until the Cock-crowing, called the <hi>middle</hi> watch, <hi>Judg.</hi> 7.19. and the third watch was from the Cock-crowing till Sun-rising, called the Morning watch, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.24. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Hebrew Dialect and Division of the <hi>Mystical</hi> Night in this Parable, the Time of this Duty to be attended was the Morning watch, for <hi>midnight</hi> was past, and the Day of Christ was dawning, or near ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, Behold the Bridegroom comes; wath ye therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as they, <hi>Psal.</hi> 130.5, 6.</p>
               <p>Querie. <hi>Watchmen, What of the Night?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answer.</hi> The Morning cometh, and also the Night, Isa. 21.12. <hi>If ye will enquire, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ye,</hi> &amp;c. viz. That Morning when the Righteous shall have the Dominion, <hi>Psal.</hi> 49.14 And also the Night, even that Night of <hi>Mystical Babylons</hi> Destruction, foretold <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.8, 10, 19, 21, 22, 23.</p>
               <p>But more particularly, That we may the better understand, what Time of the <hi>mystical</hi> Night it is with us in our Land-Horison, it
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:45884:70"/> may be considered, That after that fair Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shine DAY of the Gospel, <hi>in the dayes of Christ and his Apostles</hi> h<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d continued for some Years, a Night of great Darkness and bloody Persecution began, which continued to the Reign of <hi>Constantine</hi> the great; And that was the first Watch of our <hi>mystical</hi> Night. And after the Moonshine Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion during <hi>Constantines</hi> time, the <hi>Arian</hi> Clouds of mystical Darkness, overspread the face of the Ecclesiastical Heavens, and at last the Beast opened the Bottomless pit, and there arose a smoak out of the pit, as the smoak of a great furnace, and the Sun and the Aire were darkened, by reason of the smoak of the Pit, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.1, 2, 3. and this dark midnight dispensation, will continue till within 3 or 4 Hours of the Sun-rising: And this is the second watch of the <hi>Mystical</hi> Night of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and Persecution. So that the Morning watch is the third and next, which will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue till the Sun of Righteousness arise; which watch will begin at, or about the time of the Beasts killing Christs witnesses, and will continue about 3 ½ prophetical dayes, <hi>of years,,</hi> Rev. 11.7, 11, 15. During that time of the Witnesses lying dead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8, 9. the wise Virgins are commanded to Watch, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.13.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:45884:70"/>
               <p>And they ought to be <hi>in a watching Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture, that is to say,</hi> waking, waiting, looking, longing for and believing the near approach and suddain coming of the Bridegroom, <hi>namely,</hi> our Lord Jesus Christ. And also <hi>about watching work;</hi> to wit, doing the work of their Generation; in bearing their wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for Christ, against Anti-Christ his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry, Magistracy, Churches, Worship, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Discipline, and in finishing their Testimony of the Kingdom and Dominion of Christ, against the Kingdom and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Anti-christ. That when Christ comes and finds them so doing, he may say, Well done good and faithful Servants, enter ye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the joyes of your Master. So the wise Virgins being thus prepared and ready, they may enter into the Marriage Chamber with the Bridegroom when he comes.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>